<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the masse the fruite thereof, the cause and the meane, wherefore and howe it ought to be maynteyned. Newly perused and augmented by the first author therof. Maister Anthony Marcort at Geneue. Tra[n]slated newly out of French into Englishe. Anno M.D.XLvii.</title>
            <title>Petit traicté de la Sainte Eucharistie. English</title>
            <author>Marcourt, Antoine de, d. ca. 1560.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1547</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 111 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06882</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17314</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103750</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839495</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839495</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3923</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06882)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3923)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 56:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the masse the fruite thereof, the cause and the meane, wherefore and howe it ought to be maynteyned. Newly perused and augmented by the first author therof. Maister Anthony Marcort at Geneue. Tra[n]slated newly out of French into Englishe. Anno M.D.XLvii.</title>
                  <title>Petit traicté de la Sainte Eucharistie. English</title>
                  <author>Marcourt, Antoine de, d. ca. 1560.</author>
                  <author>Vingle, Pierre de, attributed name. aut</author>
                  <author>Viret, Pierre, 1511-1571, attributed name. aut</author>
                  <author>Geranius, Cephas. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By H. Lufte [i.e. London, J. Day],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Printed at Wittenberge :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDXLVII. [1547]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D(-D8).</note>
                  <note>Imprint false; actual imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Edited by Pierre Viret, or possibly Pierre de Vingle, under the pseudonym Cephas Geranius.</note>
                  <note>A translation of: Antoine Marcort.  Petit traicté de la Sainte Eucharistie.</note>
                  <note>Some print slightly faded.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mass --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3923:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3923:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A declaration of the Maſſe, the fruite ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the cauſe and the meane, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and howe it ought to be maynteyned.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Newly peruſed and augmented by the firſt author therof.</p>
            <p>¶ Maiſter Anthony Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cort at Geneue.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Iohn .vi.</bibl>
               <p>☞ I am the breade of lyfe, who ſo cometh to me ſhall haue no hunger. And who that beleueth in me ſhall neuer haue thurſte.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlated newly out of French into Engliſhe. Anno M.DXLvii.</p>
            <q>
               <l>☞ Reade me firſte from toppe to too</l>
               <l>And afterward iudge me a friende or a foe.</l>
               <l>If you do iudge me or I be tryed,</l>
               <l>You ſhalbe blamed when you are ſpied.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3923:2"/>
            <head>¶ Cephas Geranius to the reader.</head>
            <p>AFter that I had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered the great &amp; horrible blaſphemy preſently commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted agaynſt the holy inſtitution of the ſupper of Ieſus Chriſt, In the ſteade wherof to vs is propoſed a thynge that is fei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and found to the great diſhonor of Ieſus Chryſte and of his churche, we haue obteyned thys preſent boke of the author for to declare the ignoraunce and ſimplicitie of many. And to put away the abuſe &amp; preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pcious aſſertion of other. But for as much as the ſaid treaty is ſubmitted to the iudgement of all perſones, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge whom is great varyaunce in gyuynge ſentence at a bluſſhe, as wyllynge to eſteme of the porcion as of the hole boke. But fyrſte to reade it al through, vnderſtande it, and examin it, and that by the holy ſcripture, by the which al thyng ought to be ruled, eſtemed and weied and than to iudge Or els as ſayeth the Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſulte in the treaty <hi>De ſegibus.</hi> It is a thing inciuile wythout to haue ſeen all the lawe to iudge or anſwere to a parte therof. Alſo ſaynt Hilary in the boke of the <hi>Trinitie</hi> deſired that it ſhoulde not be condempned before that they had read that whiche he had wrytten, and alſo not to haue regard to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fautors of the errours whyche are here vanquiſhed. For as ſayth the Cann. ſuſpect .iii. queſt. The foes and aduerſe parties ought not to be iudges, by meane wher of it is neceſſary they learne to iudge them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and as before god, eſtemyng that the ſame is veritie, after the which we ſhalbe al iudged by Ieſus Chriſte from the hygh eſtates to the lowe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:3923:2"/>
            <head>The preface of the authour.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E haue the words of the prophetes ſtedfaſtly, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture the which ye ought to regarde as to the ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dle ſhinynge in a darke place, vnto the tyme that the daye begynne to gyue light, and that the day ſterre ariſe in your her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. And fyrſte vnderſtande thys that the holy ſcripture is not knowen by our owne expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For the prophecy was not gyuen in one tyme by the wyll of man.<note place="margin">ii. Peter .i.</note> But the holy men of God, inſpired of the holy gooſte haue ſpoken it. And therefore (as ſaynte Paule ſayeth) all ſcripture diuinely inſpired is behouefull to be taughte, for to reproue, to correcte,<note place="margin">ii. Tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. iii</note> and to be ſhewed in iuſtice, bycauſe that the man of god may be enti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rly inſtructed to al good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, by the which ſo many euident textes vnto vs is apparently ſhewed that the rule of oure fayth is the onely and holy word of God. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the whiche onely we ought al to beleue and keepe in all that concerneth God and oure ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. Whereunto by greate fidelitie exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs the holy Apoſtle of Ieſu Chriſte ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in thys maner.<note place="margin">Phillip. iii.</note> Procede we in one ſelf rule whereunto we be comen, bycauſe that we may be all one. Nowe it is certeyne that in folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge the opinions and fantaſies of men (the which are ſo variable, and contrary eche vnto other) that neuer we may be of one accorde but it is behouefull for vs to take one ſoole ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for our lyght and bryghtnes, for oure di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and leadynge. The whyche alone to be oure perfite and entier rule whych can not nor
<pb facs="tcp:3923:3"/>ought to be any other than the onely worde of God. For aſmuche as therein is conteyned the diuine thynges.<note place="margin">Pſa. cxvi. Roma. iii. Gala. vi.</note> Euery man is a lyer, and the only god is true. Werfore ryght wel co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cludeth the ſayde holy apoſtle y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whoſoeuer foloweth this rule peace ſhalbe ouer them and mercy. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them ſayth he, and not ouer the other, for there is but one only waye of ſaluacion.</p>
            <p>It is than right euident that the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is the onely ſtone and foundation of oure ſayth by ſuch wiſe that we ought not for to be leue,<note place="margin">Math.</note> nor hold any thing whatſoeuer it be, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the diuine thinges, but as it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teined in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcripture, without chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging any thing, adding or miniſhing, Otherwiſe it ſhoulde bee no more fayth, but foliſh opinion, imaginacion dreme error, deſceit, &amp; knaueri. Therfor it is not behoueful for any creature to vndertake for to adde, inuent, chaunge, or diminiſh whatſoeuer thing of the ſayd holi &amp; immaculate worde, but in al and ouer all it ought to be taken &amp; lefte in the right purety and clere ſimplicite wythout pluckinge (as thy fantaſi is) to other ſens tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the holy ſpirite, hath reueiled it, and that vpon payne of eternall malediction, yea &amp; if it were an angel of heauen. And here againſt muſt not be alleged tyme nor cuſtome to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary,<note place="margin">Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a. i.</note> how long ſoeuer they be,<note place="margin">Apoca.</note> or may be, for as much as the Lorde God is immutable wherby the right diuinitie can neuer be abrogated, nether by lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g antiquite of tyme nor moued or chaunged by tradicions, or conſtitutions of man. For the worde of God remayneth ſtedfaſt euerlaſting,<note place="margin">Eſaie. xl</note> permanent &amp; true, &amp; no power maye to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. And if any that by ſome ſpace of tyme haue liued, haue preched, write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diffined beleued
<pb facs="tcp:3923:3"/>and taught otherwiſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſaid holy worde bereth or conteyneth, it is nothing worthy of allegacion, for be the tyme neuer ſo longe, it is nothinge eſtemed or reputed in the preſence of God as it is writen.<note place="margin">Pſal. xi.ii. Pet. iii.</note> A. M. yeres in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſence of God is as a daye paſſed that is to ſay as no thing, or a veri ſmal thinge. ¶ Moreouer God hath ordeyned tyme behouefull at hys owne good pleaſure,<note place="margin">Roma. i.</note> wherin he hath determined reue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led, and manifeſted his verite. The which time can nether be forthered nor hyndred. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe of God is vnmouable, whyche he hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly ſhewed and declared in the temporal and holy natiuite of his ſonne, the which came not incontinent after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tranſgreſſion of Adam but taried longe tyme, and by the ſpace of thre. M. yeres dyd leaue the worlde in idolatry. Thys notwithſtanding whan the plenitude of tyme ordeined of God was occo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhed, than he ſent his ſonne made of a woman, made vnder the law, to thend that he ſhould agayne,<note place="margin">Gala. iiii.</note> bye them that were vnder the lawe.</p>
            <p>Nowe after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath done to vs this great mercy, ſhoulde it not be a greate pride and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vnkindnes in ſtead to giue him graces and thankes for ſuch a benigne and charytable di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection (for the which he gaue his onely ſonne) to ſay, wherefore taried he ſo long? why came he no ſoner? I haue ſpoken this for to touche and abate the ingratitude and arrogaunce of many poore blynde perſones the which at this preſent tyme (to whom it hath pleaſed God by his infinite bounty, many feſting him ſelfe by his holy worde and goſpell of ſaluacion, the whych a certayn of tyme by the permiſſion of tyme was diſpiſed, contemned. caſte vnder fote
<pb facs="tcp:3923:4"/>corrupt &amp; put in forgetfulnes) ſai theſe wordes of plaſphemy, or other like, and wherfore hath he taried ſo longe wherfore ſhewed he thys no ſoner? Haue not our predeceſſors lyued well? It ſuffiſeth vs to lyue as they ded, ſo many great clerkes &amp; wiſe folkes folowing the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailes and determinacions of the vniuerſities, the Cerimonies and ordynaunces of the Pope may they fayle? which be wordes of ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t folkes, or mockers, hard hertedand obſtynate. By y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which wordes their ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſo clerely doeth ſhew, that it is noyeſome, as touchinge the miſteries of God.</p>
            <p>They vnderſtand nothing but by infidelite, beinge put in reproued ſences w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out teare or re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerence, preferring horible blaſphemes, whiche is a ſigne of the yre and furor of God, decla, ryng vpon ſuche folkes ineuitable ruyne, and moſt dredfull damnacyon. Alſo all ſuche wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and allegacions vene inutile &amp; vaine with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any efficace, for the Turkes and Saraſins wyl ſay aſmuch of their lawe. Than we muſte mekely tak and receiue the gift &amp; grate of God at ſuche tyme as hys good pleaſure is to gyue it vs, without diſputing, wherfore he hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried tyll now, wyth out allegyng multitude or puralite of perſones, nor alſo ſpeke of the life, or ende of them that haue leued here to fore.</p>
            <p>For God is mighti to diſpoſe his creatures at his wil, &amp; and no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may ſay: wherfore doſt thou ſo. More ouer it were better to folowe the onely Myche hauyng the ſpirite of God,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. ii.</note> than all the ſacrifiers &amp; Prophetes of Baall, hauing the ſpirite of errour.<note place="margin">ii. Reg. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> Howe be it I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uele ſtedfaſtly that if in the time paſt the euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelike truth had ben thus'ſhewed as it is now
<pb facs="tcp:3923:4"/>that many of our predeceſſours would rather haue indeuored them mekdly and faithfully to haue receiued it, beter tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we do now, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world is ſo peruerted and corrupt by the doctrine of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which is a leuin of the Phariſes,<note place="margin">Ma. xxvi.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which Ieſus Chriſt admoniſheth vs to e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>chue &amp; flee.<note place="margin">Mark. viii.</note> Neuertheles we muſt not for the hardnes and malice of ſome aduerſaries and enimies of the truth,<note place="margin">Actes. iii.</note> leaue to declare and manifeſt aſmuch as ſhalbe poſſible the pure &amp; true worde of God. In the which without any doubt, al they ſhall beleue that be ordeyned to the life eternal, and none other &amp; all to the honor glory and prayſe of god To the which thynge as true, and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to him we ought to procur, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ſparing anye thinge, or in aniwiſe to diſſimule</p>
            <p>This is for an aduertiſment that in this pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t mater it behoueth eche one to ſtay wholy to the holy word of god, as to that wherby al cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures ſhalbe iudged. All thing ought to be exa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mined and proued, and none maye contrary it Now for to touch y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> purpoſe wherof preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly we treate. It is nedefull by holy ſcriptures to declare and euidently to ſhewe: how the maſſe ordeined of the Pope and Biſhops, and other parſones whiche in greate pride againſte right and reaſon named them ſelfe of the church, is directly againſt verite, &amp; manifeſtly againſt the holy worde of God. And therfore it is an abho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minoble thyng that ought not to be permitted to endure, by cauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> by the ſame the Lord god is greatly offended, And the moſt parte of the world vnhappily ſeduced and begiled, The whiche maſſe vnder ſhadow &amp; colour of holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, the more eaſily to ſeduſe and deceyue the world, hath ben brought, and thus cautelouſly
<pb facs="tcp:3923:5"/>compaſſed not by holy ſcripture. Wherin can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not onely be founde the name of maſſe. But by ſondri Popes and Biſhops with other lyke it hath ben founde, and put in the ſtead of the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſupper of Ieſus Chriſt, of the holy table of the precious &amp; holy bread of tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keſgeuinge the which ought to be taken of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation of al faythful Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> people, in minde &amp; recorda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the death and paſſion of Ieſus Chriſt, in remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce alſo of the charite &amp; dilection wherwith he loued vs ſo muche that he gaue his lyfe for vs Lykewiſe in ſignificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the charite and loue fraternall, wherby we ought to loue eche other, as members of the bodye of Ieſus Chriſte.</p>
            <p>In the ſtead of the whyche ſo ſalutary and, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolable inſtitucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pious Ceremony for theyr pleaſure they haue cauſed vs for to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip a lytell bread, as if it were the very God, wherin all idolatry, al iniquite, and wickednes is reiſed. And this haue they done, the better to authoriſe theyr reygne and lordeſhipe, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to exerciſe theyr tiranny, the more eaſily to make marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diſes of our ſoules, &amp; deuour the ſubſtaunce of the people, &amp; finally to cauſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes to be worſhipped. For as people effron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted without ſhame hauing harlots foreheades, they durſt well ſay, &amp; publy ſhed that they were more worthy than angels or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> virgin Marye. Becauſe that if one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (albeit that he is in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fect, &amp; a harlot full of filthines) helde a morcell of breade in his hande he hath the power (if he wil) furth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wythout declaration at his onely worde there to cauſe the ſonne of god to come and deſcende in body and in ſoule all a lyue, as byg and as hole as he hanged on the croſſe
<pb facs="tcp:3923:5"/>to beare him here &amp; there, to kepe him in a boxe or an almery, to eate hym &amp; ſwalow him whan he liſt. To be ſhort, and let him do what he wil, it is an horrible thinge to thinke on it. And if they be demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded from whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s they haue &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this merueilous power more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other that be not diſguiſed, anointed, ſhorne or cliped. They anſwere better tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they wene. For they ſay it is bycauſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> caracter, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, the toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; meruelous marke wher w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> they be ſygned, but if they thoughte well on that, that they do ſay, truly ſhame and feare would ſtyll them. For it is wrytten that none maye cheapen, ſell nor bye but he haue the marke of the beaſte.<note place="margin">Apoc. viii.</note>
            </p>
            <p>How be it becauſe that our mater may be wel builded, clerely vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; proued. It is nece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to touche, declare and ſhewe in perticuler ſome pointes of abhominacion that be foſid in this maſſe. For to ſhew all it is almoſt impoſſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble, and I beleue that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can do it, &amp; if any hade power gyuen for to do it, it behoueth hym to haue a very great boke, ſo much maledictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is encloſed therin, &amp; deteſtable perdition. Not withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> to many it ſemeth precious and fayre But as it is writen in S. Luke. That which is high vnto me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Luce. xvi</note> is abhomination afore God. And S. Paul dare wel ſai y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the angel of ſatha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tranſ figureth him ſelfe in to an angel of lighte,<note place="margin">ii. Cor. xi.</note> The whiche in this place is veri greatly fulfylled, whan vnder the ſhaddowe of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, vnder apparaunce of veritie, ſomuche li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge and falſenes in hypocriſie is founde and whiche is worſt of all, this euyll is ſo greatlye ſhed, this canker is ſo much ſowen through all the body of chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dom. Thys miſerable herbe
<pb facs="tcp:3923:6"/>hath ſpred the rotes ſo farre, that vnto man it is impoſſible to remedy it, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which is impo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſſible to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is eaſy to the Lord God. Therfore retourne we to hym, and wyth a meke herte pray we him that it wil pleaſe him to be hold vs in his mercy,<note place="margin">Luke. xviii</note> giue vs his bleſſing, and open oure eyes in ſuche wiſe that we maye clearely knowe the veryte, Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="declaration">
            <head>☞ Firſt a declaration of the daylye ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice that the ſacrifiers gyue to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowlege in theyr maſſe to be done for the ſaluation of the people.</head>
            <p>THeſe ſacrifiers than as not content with the volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tary &amp; holy ſacrifice, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the which Ieſus Chriſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he veri lambe &amp; moſt holy innocent, &amp; wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpot y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which alone taketh away the ſinnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde, hath offered for vs to God his father him ſelfe hath giuen his life,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on. i</note> &amp; ſhed his bloude for our redemcion, making an ende &amp; conſummacion of all outward &amp; viſible ſacrifice, yet as reputing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t putting them ſelfe in the ſteade of Ieſus Chriſte, they haue a maſſe, or in their maſſe made &amp; inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted a viſible ſacrifice as thei haue ſayd vtile and pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fitable for the redempcion aſwell of the quicke as the deed, which is playnly agaynſt the holy ſcripture and an outragious co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and a right renouncing of the death and paſſion of Ieſus Chriſt, which ſhortli is eaſy to be ſhewed</p>
            <p>In the .vii. Chapiter of the epiſtle to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews, in ſpekinge of Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ebre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. vii.</note> among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinges it is writen. It was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenable to haue a byſhop, holy, innocent ſeperat from ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes,
<pb facs="tcp:3923:6"/>and hygher than the ſkyes. That is to ſay ouerpaſſinge al vertue and power of pure cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures, the whiche hath no ned (as the prieſtes) to offer euery daye ſacrifice, firſt for hys ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after for the ſinnes of the people. For he hath doone thys, in offering hym ſelfe once. Notably he hath done in offering him ſelf one time, for neuer was ſuche an oblation, nor ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhalbe againe, but as fully ſufficient hathe for euer in al fuffiſed once for al.</p>
            <p>In the .ix. Chapter of that ſame epiſtel it is ſayde thus.<note place="margin">Bebrue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. ix</note> Chriſte being the high priſt of the good thinges to com, entred in bi agreater &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fiter tabernacle, not made w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> handes, that is to ſay, not of this creacion, and not by the bloud of gotes or of calues, but bi his owne precious bloude is once entred in to the ſayntuary and hath founde eternal redempcion.</p>
            <p>Here agayne he ſaith, that by his preſenting ones, eternal redemption is made and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed. Wherby it is very euident that for our redemption we haue no nede of theſe poore ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifiers, offring and ſacrifieng dayly for them ſelfe, and for vs, as if they were our redemers Therfore if we will not renounce the oblacion of Ieſus chriſt, or repuete the ſame vnſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t whiche is clere and manifeſt by the texte of the ſame Chap as it is ſayd afterwarde. Ieſus is not entred in to the ſanctuary made with han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des (which ar but ſimilytudes of true things) but chefly in heauen to thend that nowe he mai appeare for vs before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> face of his father. And not bycauſe that he offred not him ſelfe often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes for (he ſayth after) he ſhoulde haue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered often ſith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, But now in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worldes he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered
<pb facs="tcp:3923:7"/>by his ſacrifice, for the deſtruction of ſynne, and as it is ordeyned of men for to dye once, &amp; after that cometh the iudgement. Euen ſo hath Chriſt bene offered once to abolyſh the ſynnes of many. Here is certaynly a very expreſſe text where it ſayth clerely that Ieſus Chriſte offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not hym ſelfe many tymes, or other wyſe he ſhoulde dye many tymes. For Ieſus Chriſt to dye and to be offered to his father is all one.<note place="margin">Chriſtunt mori et <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>udent preſentati idem.</note> Now he ſhal neuer dye, wherby he ſhal neuer be ſacrified, and in ſacrifice he wyll neuer of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre hym ſelfe. Than it foloweth well that men can not offre and ſacrifye hym. For yf he offre not hymſelfe, howe may other offre hym.</p>
            <p>☞ And it may not be ſayd that the ſacrifice that is made nowe is the memory of that firſt ſacrifice. Wherby moreouer it foloweth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all our ſacrifiers that make the people to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that they preſent and make ſacrifice for the quycke and for the dead. Yea and yet to be the more galant, only for them that they pleaſe to chuſe and name. Therefore it appeareth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly that thei be ſeductors, begilers, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. For certainly by the death of Ieſus Chriſt all viſible ſacrifice is ceaſed, and the ſtate of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifiers is exſpired. Wherfore they are ſhorne in vaine, and dyſguyſed for nothyng elles but that they may be knowen for to be fooles vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wytty, and voyed of all brayne But for more ample probation it behoueth to conſyder the .x. chap. of the ſame epiſtle,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bre. x.</note> where as almoſt ouer al is made mencion of the holy ſacrifice of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt the whych hath made an ende of all ſacrifices, ſo that neuer a ſacrifice viſible abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth. And among other thynges it is ſayd thus in the perſon of Chriſt.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bre. x. pſ. xxxix</note> Behold I come Lorde
<pb facs="tcp:3923:7"/>God to thende that I maye do thy wyll, than foloweth. By the which wyll we be ſanctified by the oblation of the bodye of Ieſus Chriſte once for al. Than after it ſayth. For by one ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lation he hath made for euer them that are ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified perfit. And alſo the holy goſt teſtifieth it. For after he ſayth. I ſhal haue nomore mynde of theire ſynnes nor of their iniquities. And where there is remiſſion of them there is no more oblation for the ſynne.</p>
            <p>☞ And for bycauſe that excuſe of ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce be not in vs, lette vs conſider what theſe pore ſanctifiers heretofore haue ſayed. That verie true it is that Ieſus Chriſt had gyuen his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die in ſacrifice, principally for the ſynne of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam (and as they ſaye) for originall ſynne, but not entierly for ſinnes that be committed actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, daye by daye, whiche is none other thinge but for to ſaye and blaſpheme that our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte hath not made and founde en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier and perfite redemption. And therfore they ſaye (as if they were adioyned or knitte wyth Ieſus Chriſte, for to healpe him to make oure redemption, and that they were our redemers, that they offer to Gdd in theyr maſſe, a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for the remiſſion of our ſynnes, whiche is a merueylous boldnes, and a vnhappy arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaunce. For the which to abate and put doune in the ſayed chaptre, forthwyth it ſayeth after thys maner. Yf we ſinne willyngly after that we haue receyued knowledge of veritie, there is lefte vs no more ſacrifice for ſynnes. The which wordes (in whatſoeuer maner that any wyl take them) be ſo cleare, ſo quicke &amp; migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that they can not be ynough merueiled at, howe the worlde hath ben ſo abuſed, blynded.
<pb facs="tcp:3923:8"/>and deceyued to ſuffre as yet willyngly ſuche ſacrifice, or to preſente any ſacrifice viſible and outward vnto the Lord God for our ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ſeynge that ſo conſtantly, ſo myghtyly, ſo many tymes and often the ſayed holy Apoſtle affirmeth and ſaith that there is no more ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fice, nor neuer ſhal be. For after Ieſus Chriſte it behoueth not to loke for any other ſacrifier. But it hath behoued, and ſo god hath permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that Sata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by hym and hys miniſters haue ſeduced the worlde a fewe excepte. For it was a fore ſpoken and prophecyed that all ſhoulde be thus waſted &amp; loſt.<note place="margin">Mat. xxiiii</note> And finally for to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſte the power, glory and magnificence of the ſouereigne Lorde, the whych by the ſounde of his word,<note place="margin">ii. Theff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. ii.</note> and by the ſpirite of his mouth, ſhall put to ruyne and ouerthrowe the reygne of his enemyes, that is to wyt, Antychriſt, the worlde hell, and Satan.</p>
            <p>☞ Alas is not thys a greate miſery to thys vnhappy worlde, to haue ſo greatly diſpiſed theſe fore alleged ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, to haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tempned them in this wyſe, &amp; ſo coldly paſſed them ouer withoutany other aduiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, neuer willing to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider that there is great differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betwene ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crifice and teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. For wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we offre a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to God, we gyue a preſent to him wherby it is verye euident that whan we take and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue of hym any thyng, that it is no ſacrifice but a liberall gyfte and pure mercy.</p>
            <p>☞ And who than is ſo blynded that he ſeeth not here clearly that by gift of a teſtament, con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>firmed by the death of the teſtatour by greate loue and charite, he hath wholy giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him ſelfe vnto vs? Saint Luke toucheth it at the quicke when he ſayth thus.<note place="margin">Luke. xxii</note> Thys chalice is the newe
<pb facs="tcp:3923:8"/>teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in my bloud that ſhalbe ſhed for you. Teſtament he ſayeth, not example to do ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. At thys poynt they haue very ill thought, whan by forgetfulnes (to the ende that I ſaye not my ſunderſtanding) ſuche a gyft they haue wylled to chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge into ſacrifice. Yf we wyl do ſacrifice let vs do that ſaynt Paule ſayth and beleue his diuine counſel, where he ſayth thus.<note place="margin">Roma. xii.</note> I praye you than my brethren by the mercy of God, that ye offre your bodyes in a liuely ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fice, holily. pleaſaunt to God. &amp;c. To ſuch ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fice we be all ordeyned of God, prieſtes &amp; kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges without beyng ſhauen, ſhorne, ceremonies or dyſguyſed. Not for to offre his ſonne vnto hym agayne. For to offre vnto him ſuche offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng we be to vnworthy, to vile and infecte, foraſmuche as he offered hym ſelfe to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for vs.</p>
            <p>☞ The which oblation for al times is ryght ſufficient and perfyte, or elles it behoued for to reiterate or renew it becauſe it ſhould be vnperfite, or elles certainly inconuenient to ſeeke any other, whych by ſtronge argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. I ſhewe thus.</p>
            <p>☞ In the epiſtle to the Hebrewes by diuers argumentes it is concluded that for the death of an high Biſhop there muſt an other be ordei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned and by the death of hym another,<note place="margin">Hebrues .x.</note> &amp; ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently vnto the tyme that there come one entyerly immortall, whych is oure onely medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atour Ieſus Chriſte.<note place="margin">Note this.</note> The whiche alway aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth for vs in the preſence of God. Lykewyſe for the imperfection of the ſacrifices of the ☜. olde law it behoued euery day to beginne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the tyme that one was offered entyerly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite and conſummate, which muſt not be renu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.
<pb facs="tcp:3923:9"/>The whyche moſte holy and moſte perfyte hath be made by our high Biſhop and paſtour Ieſus Chriſt whych offered him ſelfe in ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and none other thing no better thynge nor none ſo good could be found next God. Al this is declared more at large in the .v. vi. viii. and .x chapitres of the ſaid epiſtle.</p>
            <p>☞ Now I demaund of all ſacrifiers if the ſacrifice be perfite or vnperfite wherefore ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe they thus the pore worlde,<note place="margin">No eſt da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re me di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t.</note> and ſel a thinge that is nothynge worth. If it be perfitte, why is it dayly renued, and ſo often times by thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſandes begonne agayne. Put your ſelfe forth poore ſacrififiers, and if ye haue power to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, anſwer, for gladly I woulde vpon this heare your anſwer.<note place="margin">i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>q. neuer.</note> The which I knowe that ☞ ye wyl bring forth ad Calendas grecas, that is to ſay neuer, after your honeſt cuſtome.</p>
            <p>☞ For the whiche thinges that be ſo euident and manifeſte that any man ought to be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to ſaye the contrary, ſome wyly foxes all aſhamed of theyr matter, to couer and excuſe theyr malyce to abuſe and begyle the worlde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine (as theyr maner hath ben and is alwaies to reſiſte and gainſey the veritie (as nowe are many not aſhamed to ſpeake &amp; properly to ſay they haue not done ſacrifice, but onely haue offered ſacrifice of prayſe whiche is openly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the Canon of theyr maſſe by the which they name and call this breade (after that they haue pronounced the wordes which they call ſacramentalles) holy ſacrifice, holy oblation, preſented and giuen to God as the ſacrifice of Abell and Abraham. and commonly they call it Corpus domini, the holy hooſte and ſuche ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of names.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3923:9"/>
            <p>☞ Alſo for to pray to God and offre to hym a ſacrament of prayſe needeth neyther breade nor wine, there needeth neither light nor ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dle, ſhauyng or ſheryng, nor diguyſyng w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vnaccu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed and wy de garmentes, wherby they can no longer couer theyr abuſe, theyr malyce and errours by ſuche fictions and legerdemaynes wherby alwaies they diſtroye them ſelues, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge ſo litle wytte that in ſo ſpeakyng, they confounde it wholy them ſelues. For ſacrifice of prayſe is comen to all perſones. Be it man woman, or chylde they are all bounde to offre ſacrifice of prayſe. And by thys meanes if in theyr maſſe be none other ſacrifice but prayſe a woman myght ſay it, yea a litle childe, which is directly agaynſte the accuſtomed doctrine. But it muſte needes be that ſuche lyinge drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes diſtroye it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>☞ Now haue they ſayd ouer al vniuerſities Papalles that the maſſe ſayde or ſonge by an vnthryfty harlotte prieſt, was, and is as good, as the maſſe of the mooſte holy prieſte, that is. The which thing we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe to be more verifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they wene. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both is but wretchydnes, howbeit theyr intention is to ſay that, that cometh not of the vertue of him that doeth ſuche worke, but by the vertue of the thinge wrought. that is to ſay, offered to God ſacrificed and preſentyng, and in theyr Latine they do ſay. Non virtute operis operantis: ſed virtute operis operati, that is to ſaye, not by the vertue of the worke of the worker but by the vertue of the worke wroughte which is all falſhode, dreames, and inuentions of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue is effectually ſhewed.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:3923:10"/>
            <head>¶ The ſeconde declaration is if in the Sacramente of breade and wyne there is tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanciation or not.</head>
            <p>FOr thermore to confounde erroure after erroure, notwythſtandynge that thys fyrſte poynte is ſufficient to aboliſhe it euidently. I meane not the Sacramente of Ieſus Chriſte, for it beſemeth me not but thys triumphaunte Papall Maſſe. The ſayd ſelye poore ſacrifiers as enchauntours and idle people whiche neuer eſtemed the holy ſcriptures, and for to encreaſe &amp; publyſhe theyr foly ſhe frenaſy, ſcantly wyllyng to gyue place to the body of Ieſus Chriſte, haue ſayed, put in wrytynge, preached and taught. That after that they had blowen or ſpoken ouer the bread whiche they holde betwene their fingers, and alſo ouer the wyne that they put in the chalice, that there remayneth neyther breade nor wyne but by tranſformation, or as they ſaye tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtanciation, the body of Ieſus Chriſte is ther vnder the accide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of the bread inuiſibly hyd. And the bloud alſo vnder the accide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of the wyne, beinge there no more bread or wine which is a doctrine of deuyls, agaynſt al veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, agaynſt al experience, agaynſte reaſon, and holy ſcripture, the whiche hath amonge other thinges caſt away &amp; alienated from the chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> law and religion almoſt al the earth, ſo ful of wretchednes is the papyſticall doctrine.</p>
            <p>☞ That this doctrine and ſophiſtical deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination proceading of vanitie &amp; of dreames is entierly againſt the holy ſcriptures, it is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and manifeſt by, S. Paul, S. Mathew, S. Marke, &amp; S. Luke. Where as al theſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes
<pb facs="tcp:3923:10"/>of truth ſpeake of the holy ſupper of Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, they haue ſayd and put in wryting that oure Lord Ieſus Chriſte toke breade and breake it diſtributynge it to his Apoſtles and diſciples. Fyrſte S. Paule ſayeth thus.<note place="margin">i. Cori. xi,</note> Oure Lorde Ieſus Chriſte the ſame nyght in which he was betrayed, toke breade and geuyng tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes brake it and ſayed. Take and eate, thys is my body whiche is broken for you. S. Mat. lykewyſe ſayeth in thys maner.<note place="margin">Ma. xxvi</note> And as they ſupped. Ieſus toke bread, bleſſed it, and brake it, and gaue it to his diſciples and ſayed Take and eate, thys is my bodie.<note place="margin">Ma. xiiii.</note> Saint Marke alſo and S. Luke haue written it in their Goſpels,<note place="margin">Luk. xvi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> where as they name the breade expreſſely, and not the ſubſtaunce of breade. Item S. Paule in the place before alledged, after that he had made ample mention of the inſtitution and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunce of the holy ſupper of Ieſus Chriſte, ſayd in this maner. Man approueth him ſelfe, and ſo eateth of this breade, &amp; drinketh of the chalice, where as he ſaythe not. Eate ye the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of Ieſus Chriſte, whiche is hyd vnder the apparance of breade, but openly, purely, &amp; ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply he ſayed, eate ye of this breade. Now it is certaine that the ſcripture hath no diſſceyt and that in it is no fainyng And notwithſtandyng this the poore blynd folke haue ben preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and bolde that they durſt diffine &amp; deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine agaynſt ſaint Paule, and other euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtes that there is neither bread nor wyne, but onely the ſimilitude of bread and wine. Alſo in the Actes of the apoſtles it is writen thus.<note place="margin">After. x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> And on a Sabboth daye, when we were aſſembled to breake bread, where as it is not writen ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blaunce or likenes of breade. And S. Paule in
<pb facs="tcp:3923:11"/>an other place ſaith. The bread that we dreake is it not the participatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the body of Ieſus Chriſte. In the which ſo many euident places the holy ſcripture pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth &amp; ſayth expreſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be bread, not a ſhape, or kinde, apparance, or likenes of breade. Wherfore on paine to be condemned of god, we muſt ſimply beleue it to be breade, and not lykenes of breade onely, for (as it is ſayed) in the holy ſcripture is no fei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge.</p>
            <p>☞ True it is that the fayethfull Chriſtians wel vnderſtandyng the dignitie of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente, take the breade ſacramentall, not as co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune breade, vulgare and vſuall, but as bread ſanctified, apoynted, and ordeined to diuine v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes bycauſe that in this mooſte holy action the ſpirite and ſoule of the faythfull ſhoulde be nouryſhed, that is to ſaye, knitte, ioyned, and vnied by ſpeciall operation to his propre lyfe, whiche is his paſtoure and onelye ſauiour Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and that inuiſible for the time of this mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tall lyfe, by intelligence and contemplation of fayth. To the whiche in the lyfe to come, ſhall appere without coueringe of ſacramente, ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, actually, really as our redemer, high biſhop, kynge and ſacrifier ordeined of god his father<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vnto the conſummation of all thinges.</p>
            <p>☞ Saynt Cipryan martyr, one of the au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t doctours &amp; the fathers of the church in a ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he made of the ſupper of the Lorde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth. Suſcitati Lazari. Hieroſolimis increpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erat rumor By highe and longe ſentences that whiche I haue toutched ſhortly, amonge the whiche he ſayed thus. Panem angelorum ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſacramento manducamus in terris, eundem ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſacramento manifeſtius edemus in celis.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3923:11"/>
            <p>That is to ſay, we Chriſtians eate the bread of angels, which is Chriſt the liuinge God vnder the Sacrament in earth, but we ſhall eate it in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> manifeſtly without colour of ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And what he vnderſtandeth by eatynge hym, ſelfe declareth it in the ſame ſermon, ſayinge, Quod eſt eſca carni hoc anime eſt fides, quod cibus corpori, hoc verbum ſpiritui. That is to ſaye. That, whiche the meate doth to the fleſhe the fayth doth it to the ſoule, and that whiche the meate doeth to the body, the worde of God doth it to the ſpirit. As touching the proprietie of bread it is wel to be noted. The nature and condition of breade and wine (as to theyr fyrſt conſtitution) is to nouryſh and feede the body. But it hath pleaſed the Lorde to ordeyne them in his holy Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, to another and more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent operation, which is that to the well vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandynge and faythfull perſon it bringeth and repreſenteth (not to the ſence of the body, but to the ſoule &amp; ſpirite) actual takinge quicke knowledging, and mynde of the body of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiour of our ſoules, delyuered to death for vs, and of his precious bloud ſhed for our redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, whiche be two ſundry thinges. For the bodye mighte well haue died without effuſion of bloud, as we ſe daily many dye. But by his greate mercie it pleaſed him for to do bothe for vs. That is that he hath taſted death as to the body, and not only that, but alſo woulde ſhed and offre his precious bloud in price of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion. And therfore bicauſe that in his church ſhoulde alwaye be had minde of theſe two ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable workes he hath ordeined this ſame ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſacrament, which is the conſummation and ende of all other in two viſible thinges that is
<pb facs="tcp:3923:12"/>to witte in bread and wyne, the which thinges ſhould neuer be ſeparate, as they haue done in the Popyſh churche, which is a great wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and extreme ſacrilege openly agaynſte the inſtitution and ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Ieſus, that ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>preſſely and ſo euidently had conioyned them. But what care vnkinde folke ennemies to the veritie, of the ordinaunces thereof, for they be wiſe, and not vnwitty. Yf ſaynte Paule were alyue, O how he would crie againſt ſuch a cur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed abuſe, ſo would ſaint Auſtine, S. Ciprian and all other induced with the good ſpirite.</p>
            <p>☞ But to returue to the purpoſe, it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne that of the ſame breade whiche they had vſed in eating the Lambe of paſſing, called the Paſcall lambe. Ieſus Chriſte toke, and brake, ſayeng, take, eate, this is my body. Where v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon in the ſermon afore ſayed thys good doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour Ciprian ſayd thus. Ante verba illa, cibus ille co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munis, tantum nutriendo corpori co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus erat, ſed er quo a domino dictum eſt, hoc facite in meam commemoratione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp;c. panis iſte ſolemni benedictione ſacratus, ad totiꝰ homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis vitam, ſalutem<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> proficit. That is to ſaye before the wordes of Ieſus Chriſte this meate that was commune auayled to feede the body onely. But ſyth that the lorde had ſpoken, this bread co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrate by ſolempne bliſſyng profiteth to the life and entier ſaluation of man. Thys breade than by one ſuch and ſo ſinguler appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, ſo high, ſolempne and excellent bleſſing is chaunged and altered, not in corporall ſence, but to intellectuall ſpirite, not of kinde or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce but of operation of nature, of ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, dignitie and office, yea to the faythful, but nothinge to the vnfaythful but perdition.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3923:12"/>
            <p>☞ The whyche thynge yll vnderſtande hath gyuen occacion to the ſchole men at thys pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente tyme curiouſly and vaynely to diſpute that is to wit, if the accide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes may be ſeparate &amp; remaine without ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out accidentes, &amp; other diueres allegations, which are not to the purpoſe of Ieſus Chriſte nor of his church but ſerue to confuſe the world, and to bringe the chriſten religion to ſclau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kery and irriſion, for of one inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenience (if it be not withſtande) many other will folowe.</p>
            <p>☞ Who may than any more ſuſteyne, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, and endure ſuche folke, the which as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous and arrogaunt, without feare or reuerence haue be ſo bold, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude that there is neyther breade nor wyne, but haue dreamed and inuented a wanton and a newe terme of ſpeakynge, that they haue called (as is aboue ſpoken) tranſſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiation. The whiche in the holy ſcripture was neuer reade. Nor by the ſayntes and good Fathers of the primatyue churche imagined. Whereby as enemyes of God &amp; his worde by very ryght ought to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſed, &amp; caſt awaye, or the better and fayrer to ſpeake, as piuiſhe fooles they ought to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempned and diſpiſed.</p>
            <p>☞ How be it if any ſhoulde demaunde them by what veritie ſuche a thynge is done. They wyll anſwere forthwyth, by the doctrines of theyr ſcholes, that it is in the vertue of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentall wordes, proferred and pronounced ouer the breade. In ſuche wyſe that yf there were no bodye that vnderſtode, or hearde the ſayd wordes, that neuertheles the ſayed tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation woulde folowe, ſo that the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice had his full ſtrength wyth matter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenable.
<pb facs="tcp:3923:13"/>&amp;c. But certainly I greatly wonder &amp; haue pitie on them that they be ſo blynde and haue not ſo muche vnderſtandyng to conſider that oure Lorde ſpake not to the breade whan he ſayed. Take, eate, thys is my bodye. Nor he ſpake not to the wyne. As. S. Luke reciteth whan he wrote. And toke the cup &amp; gaue than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, and ſayed. Take ye it &amp; diſtribute amonge you. Alſo afterwarde likewiſe he gaue the cup after ſupper ſayinge. Thys cuppe is the newe Teſtamente in my bloude, whiche is ſhed for you. In the whiche writynges and all other of the new teſtament this matter is very euident that he neuer ſpake to the breade nor wyne. Than it maye be well ſayed that theſe poore folke be very vnwitty, in ſecrete hidyng aſide not willynge to be hearde and vnderſtande of anye, blowe and ſpeake thus ouer the breade and wyne. Wherof oure Lorde Ieſus Chriſte neuer gaue vnto them neither exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple nor word But it is the cuſtome that alwayes one errour engendreth an other errour.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="declaration">
            <head>¶ The .iii. declaration is of the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence or corporal preſence of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente of breade and wyne at the Maſſe.</head>
            <p>IN thys poynt more than in any other they haue fayled, &amp; erred greatly, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſayd, wrote, preached, gaue to vnderſtande, and taught, that in the ſteade of bread and wyne (as they ſaye) vnder the ſhapes or kyndnes viſible, whyte or blake, yelowe or redde, it is al one, the body of Ieſus Chriſte really and in dede, entyerly, corporally &amp; perſonally in fleſhe
<pb facs="tcp:3923:13"/>and bone, as greate and perfite as preſently he lyued. And in this wiſe they haue prouoked al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooſte the vniuerſall worlde to manifeſte and open ydolatri. Agaynſt the whiche importable abuſion it behoueth to reſiſte myghtily wyth the holy ſcriptures.</p>
            <p>And fyrſte of all we muſte reteyne and note wel the artycle of our faith,<note place="margin">Rom. vii.</note> that Ieſus Chriſt died for oure ſinnes, and aroſe for oure Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.<note place="margin">ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. xvii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> And after his reſurrection aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in to heauen, and ſytteth on the right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of his father, reigninge in maieſtye, to whome al po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer is giuen, in heauen, in earth, &amp; in hel.<note place="margin">Philip. ii.</note> That he aſcended into heauen viſible in the preſence of the Apoſtles and diſciples it is certaine.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ciuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. i.</note> Of the which wonderful aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cion they were faith full and true wytneſſes,<note place="margin">Mar. xvi.</note> as it appeareth in the Act. of the Apoſtles, &amp; by S. Marke in the laſt Chap. of his Goſpell. Alſo S. Paul writinge to the Colloſſiens ſayth in thys maner.<note place="margin">Coſ. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i.</note> Yf ye be riſen wyth Chriſte, ſeke heauenly thynges that be aboue, where Chriſte is, ſytting on the ryght hande of the father. If foloweth well than, ſyth that Ieſus Chriſte is aboue in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſittynge on the right hande of his father, that he is not here in earth betwen the preiſtes handes, nor cloſed in a boxe or aulmery, for his body was neuer but in one place at once.</p>
            <p>Therefore if hys bodie be in heauen, for that tyme it is not in earth, and if he were in earth, it ſhoulde not be in heauen for of certayne a ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry perfighte bodye is but in one place at ones as I ſayde afore,<note place="margin">Caue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a ſabe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and it is no nede to dreame or allege any miracle of God, and ſaie that god is almyghtye to make it be done, and to mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplie it at ones, in ſondri places, for that is the
<pb facs="tcp:3923:14"/>rauinge ymaginacion of man wythout foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacion of ſcripture. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God maketh ſuche a multiplicacion we haue none aſſuraunce of ſcripture, nor deuine promiſe</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Argumen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a poſſe ad eſſe ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit.</note>Wherfore to ſaye. God maye do it, ergo he dothe it. That ſaynge is nothynge worth, for here is no queſtion of the power of God. And it is all certayne that God hath the power to make all the Aſſes. Horſes and Mules in the world for to ſpeake, as he made Balaams aſſe to ſpeake, howbeit he doth it not.</p>
            <p>More ouer we haue neuer red in holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that he hath multiplied &amp; put at one tyme on bodye in ſondry places But rather made it to tranſport fro one place to a nother at hys pleſure,<note place="margin">Da. xiiii.</note> as appereth of Habacuc that by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> an angell was in continent horne from Iudea in to Babilon but wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was in on place he left the other.<note place="margin">Acte. viii.</note> Likewiſe it is ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of Philip, after that he had baptiſed the gelded man a man of authorite with Candace quene of the Ethiopi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens that the ſpirite of our Lorde rauiſhed hym ſodenly, and was founde in Azoto.</p>
            <p>But that one onely bodye hath ben in ſondry places at once was neuer red. Wherefore to ſaye that God doth ſuch a miracle without ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perteining, without ſight of ani thing, without any knowlege, the foliſhe dreame is to greate. The workes of God be manifeſt, cleare, open, and certayne. He neuer did miracle on any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner body without manifeſting it. The workes of God be not couered (ſpecial whan they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne bodily thynges) but as I ſayed be cleare and open. Than to ſay and affirme ſuch a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle without euidence and ryght greate certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, is greatly to erre, and to conſtreyne the
<pb facs="tcp:3923:14"/>people to beleue, by fire, water, bloude ſheding, death, priſonme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, cordes, and hangment, is moſt cruell tiranny. Moreouer we haue infalible cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tification by the holy ſcripture, of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ing of the ſon of man, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it would pleaſe him to depart fro heauen, he ſhould be viſible &amp; mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt. For as S, Math ſayth.<note place="margin">ma. vviiii</note> Yt any ſay vnto you Chriſt is here, or there, beleue him not, for as the lyghtning iſſueth fro the orient, &amp; appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vnto the occident, ſo ſhalbe the cominge of the ſon of man. And therof the holy angels of God gaue greate witnes wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſayd to the apoſtles. Ye men of Galile, what ſtand ye ſtyl be holding the ſkye?<note place="margin">Actes .i.</note> Thys Ieſus that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued from you in to heauen, ſhal come as ye ſaw him aſcende to heauen. That is to wyte openly, viſibly, clerely, and manifeſtly, not hid, courted wrapped, or clothed wyth breade or dowghe.</p>
            <p>And if vnto all this be anſwred by ſophiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taſi, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d alonely of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> coming at the daye of iugement, &amp; not in the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, wherefore (as they ſaye) he remaineth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs in body &amp; ſoule perpetually although y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hideth him, &amp; ſheweth him not. This is a ſaing at wil wherewith they haue abuſed vs in tyme paſt whiche ſaynge was eaſy &amp; light to beleue, here before when we beleued it by the ſeduction of hypocrites</p>
            <p>Alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſaiyng is a blaſpheminge,<note place="margin">Ma. vvv?</note> &amp; maketh Ieſus Chriſt a lier. Which ſaith expreſſli, that we ſhal haue alway poore folke w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs, but we ſhall not haue him alway, The which wordes we muſt neceſſaryly vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, of his body, &amp; his humanite. For as touchinge his holy ſprite it is ouer all, &amp; alway with them that be his, as
<pb facs="tcp:3923:15"/>it is ſayd in S. Math.<note place="margin">ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. xxviii</note> Behold I am with you to the end of the worlde.</p>
            <p>Nowe is this an ouer dullynge &amp; darkening of the ſpirite &amp; vnderſtanding of the people to bind them &amp; cauſe them to ſtop and ſtey at a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell bread, at a thynge viſible and corruptible, to cauſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſeke him there, which is of ſoue rayn maieſty in triumphaunt glory. For now he is out of his tyme and out of his infirmite, and neuertheles, in the putting and holding of him without any order thus in a lu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p of dough, he ſhould be more ſet by tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euer he was in the preſence of Pilate. Yea if one woulde ſaye a furbiſher of olde baggage. Nay, like as a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minican ſaid ſomtyme, in the cite of Geneue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly preached y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he made him ſelfe as litle as a Piſmire. And if it wer not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the mater is ſo er<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſt, and that I haue dolor of the folyſhnes of ſuch one graceles. I could not abſtayne me for laughyng.</p>
            <p>But in leauinge the fooles in theyr foly, I would wite, what v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ilite or profit mighte com to vs that he were with vs in a lytel morſel of breade ſo hyd?<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>n. xvi.</note> whan he hym ſelfe ſayde, if he aſcended not to hys father that the holy. Goſt ſhoulde not come, and whan he was aſcended into heauen, that he woulde ſend him, whiche be dyd at the daye of Penthecoſt, and ſytte al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo on them that it pleaſed him.</p>
            <p>To be briefe this popiſhe doctrine is cauſe of the vniuerſall diſtruction almooſte of all the world. And they ought not for the couering of theyr yes, and the better to exercyſe thir vnſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciat auaryce, for their pryde, their marchaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, and rapine &amp; for to giue ſome apparence and colour to their mater, for to allege or bring
<pb facs="tcp:3923:15"/>furth theſe wordes. Thys is my body that is giuen for you. For by them none other thinge is ſhewed but preſence ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tal in the bread and wyne not as it hath be ſayde vulgare or commmune, but ſignificatiue and Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, which is and ought to be taken in greate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence in minde of the death and paſſion of Ieſus Chriſt, repreſentyng the brenninge loue greate charite wherwyth he loued vs, and bys holy ſpirite wherwyth he hath quickened vs.</p>
            <p>Betokenynge alſo the lone that in veri cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite we oughte to loue eche other, as membres of one bodye, wherof Ieſus Chriſt is the head and that it is ſo, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame wordes gitreth know ledge therof. For it is certaine, that, that which we do ſe that is to wyte the breade or as they ſaye the whitnes of bread, is not the bodye of Ieſus Chriſte.</p>
            <p>Therfore if any ſaye to me. It is true, that whiche is ſeen is not the bodye,<note place="margin">Theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ioy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>x c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> but vnder that or within that which is ſeen, the body is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned and encloſes. Thys is well gloſed, and thus alterynge the purpoſe, and the wordes of Ieſus Chriſt thei be nomore take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their pure<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes and ſimplicitie, as he preferred them with out gloſe or addition, for he ſayde not vnder that or wythin that is conteyned mi bodye but ſymply ſayd. Thys is my body as it was ſaid of the Paſchall lambe.<note place="margin">Exod. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> This is the paſſage of the Lorde God. And neuertheles it is very eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente that the lambe was not the paſſage, but that onely it betokened the paſſage.<note place="margin">Lamb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Paſſaige</note> In thys maner alſo the breade is not the bodye, but it ſygnifieth the bodye, as in another place it is ſayde, that Ieſus Chriſt is the ſtone,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o.</note> howbeit it is certain that he was not the ſtone,<note place="margin">i. Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> but that
<pb facs="tcp:3923:16"/>by the ſtone he was ſigninified or repreſented. To thys purpoſe ſayeth ſaynte Auſtine thus, Res ſignificantes accipiunt nomina rerum ſig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nificatorum Non enim dicitur: petra ſignifica bat Chriſtum, ſed abſolute dicitur petra erat Chriſtus. In lyke maner of ſpeakinge he ſayd I am the very vyne.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ou. xv vyne.</note> That is to wite. I am ſig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nified by the vine.</p>
            <p>☞ And aboue all thys is to be noted. For it is wryten he beleued the worde of the Lorde And it was reputed for rightuouſneſſe and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde was made betwene hym and the Lorde, of the which Iuſtyficacion and acccorde was giuen vnto hym the ſigne and token of Tircu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, and in ordeynynge the ſayde token the Lord God ſayde vnto hym. Hoc eſt pactum me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>um.<note place="margin">Gen. xvii Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> Thys is min accord or couenaunt. Howe, beit it is very cuident that the ſayd inciſion or circumciſion was not the ſayde accord or coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt but it was onely the ſigne of the accord or couenaunt Wherby if I ſhould aſke of a ler<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned perſone, the perfite vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding of theſe wordes thys is my couenaunte. He would ſay to me thys is the ſygne of my couenaunt. Like wyſe I would ſay to him of thys. Thys is mi body,<note place="margin">Ma. xxvi</note> thys is the ſygne of my body. For it is al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>one maner to ſpeake, ſo highlye and perfitlye in all thinges lyke as there is no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that could reaſonably ſay to the contrary Other textes ynought there be in holy ſcripture,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. xi.</note> where ſuch maners of ſpeaking is vſed, wherby it was not neceſſari thus hardly to take this text after the letter Hoc eſt corpus meum, that is to ſay: this is mi body without ſwet miſtical and ſpiritual knowledge, but it hath behoued ſo to do for to greace and fatte the healyes of theſe fat bulles
<pb facs="tcp:3923:16"/>and rauiſhe the worlde in admitacion.</p>
            <p>Alſo becauſe the iuel of abominacion ſhoulde bee araiſed in the holye place,<note place="margin">Pſal. xx<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Daniel. xi i. Theſſa. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the manne of pryde and of ſynne and he of whom the comminge is after the operacion of Sathan in all power and ſignes, lienge mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles and wonders, ſhoulde bee exalted and wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhipped as God.</p>
            <p>☞ Notably the holy apoſtle did ſaye, ſignes and liyng wonders. For in thys maſſe and blo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wen breade greate wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders, lowde lies he hath imagined. Is it not well dreamed, well lyed, and raued to haue ſayd that all the accidentes of the breade, and wyne as whitnes, roundes, weight, taſt, ſauor moyſtnes &amp;c. be and remain there without ſubiect, that is to wite without foundation and ſubſtaunce. Is not thys very hardily ſpoken to ſay, that they hold, that they beare, and that they cloſe the bodye of Ieſus Chriſte, all of hys heyght, all entyer, all a lyue in fleſhe and bones thus and ſo, and whither they wyll.</p>
            <p>I demaunde ones again what meaneth, &amp; wyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth this poore ſacrifier whan he pronounceth the wordes ouer the breade? ſayng. This is mi body. leuyng the reſt of the texte euangelicall, and addeth preſumptuouſly this word, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> ſayeng. Hoc eſt enim corpus meum, that is to ſaye, for thys is my body, The whiche worde, enim (or for) none of the euangelyſtes dyd adde wherin they enterpriſe vpon the worde of god Yf the ſayde ſacrifier wyll ſaye that it is hys owne body that is hid vnder this whitnes and kynde of breade, it is certaynly a foule and a ſtynkinge thinge. Yf he ſhall aunſwere that it is the body of Ieſus Chriſte, wherfore ſaith
<pb facs="tcp:3923:17"/>he not then. Hoc eſt corpus Chriſte, that is to ſay thys is the body of Chriſte. Bycauſe it myght be vnderſtande what he ſayde. And if he ſaye, that be recitethe the wordes onely or that he reciteth the wordes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ieſus putfurth takinge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> materialli, or by maner of nothing To that I anſwer, that wordes taken mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rially (by theyr owne ſchoſaſtical doctrine) ſig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyfieth nothinge.</p>
            <p>☞ Moreouer I aſke of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where thei haue promes and aſſurau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God that euery tyme and as often as they ſhal pronounce ſuch wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des that the body of Ieſus Chriſte all ſodenly ſhall deſcende betwene theyr handes. Yf they alledge thys texte Hoc facite in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>memoratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem meam, that is to ſay, do this in the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c of me: it is not anſwered to the purpoſe. For it is ryght manifeſt that he ſpeaketh not there &amp; maketh any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that he ſhould do ſacrifice,<note place="margin">ii. Cro. xi.</note> but of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meſtion and eateynge of the bread, whych ought to be done in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration of the charitie, death and paſſion of our Lord Ieſu Chriſt, in ſhewyng the ſame (as. S. Paule ſayeth) tyl that he come, that is to wyt,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of .xviii.</note> openly and manifeſtly at the great day of dome, and ought not to ſtaie ſo much at this verbe ſubſtantyue Sumes eſt, that is in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſh, am, was and is: wyllyng to conclude, that he is ther corporally, becauſe he ſayde, Hoc eſt corpus meum, this is my body. For this verbe ſubſtantiue, albeit that it is expreſſed, yet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth he not bodily preſence, but ſouerayne and ſpirituall, lyke as he ſayde. Wher two or thre be gathered together in my name there am I in the mydes of them. He ſayed expreſſely, In me dio eorum ſum. And neuertheles it is very cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne
<pb facs="tcp:3923:17"/>that he wyll gyue none other thynge to meanynge but hys gooſtly aſſiſtence, not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally, or corporally, as theſe Papiſtes haue preached that not onelye Ieſus Chriſt is there preſente really in bodye and in ſoule, but alſo (that more is) the angels and ſayntes, and all the celeſtiall court. Wherin they ſhew playnly the efficacy of their errour, wherin they be fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, and haue not ſo muche vnderſtandynge to knowe that they confounde them ſelues. For lyke as by theyr ſayinge they putte &amp; multiplye the bodye of Ieſus Chriſte in ſondry places at ones, ſo muſte it be than, that all the Aungels and all the ſayntes of God be in diuers places at ones. And if they be ſo aſhamed to conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it: I woulde lerne of them the texte of the word of God, where they fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de thys, and if it were ſo that they haue none I deteſte them as dreamers and curſed lyers.</p>
            <p>☞ And if we bringe forthe the .vi. chapitre of ſaynte Ihon, where as he ſayeth, I am the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge breade whyche is deſcended from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, if any eate of thys breade he ſhall lyue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally. And the breade that I ſhall gyue, for the lyfe of the worlde is my fleſhe. That af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde he ſayde, excepte ye ſhall eate of the fleſhe of the ſonne of man, and drynke hys bloude ye ſhall haue no lyfe in you. He that ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth my fleſſhe, and drynketh my bloude hathe lyfe euerlaſtynge, and I ſhall reyſe hym vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne in the laſte daye. For my fleſſhe is very meate and my bloude is very drynke. To thys allegation I anſwere, that in all thys Chapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Ieſus Chryſte manifeſteth and declareth, hym ſelfe ſuch as he is &amp; was, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to wyte our lyfe and onely gyuer of lyfe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3923:18"/>
            <p>☞ Moreouer he willed to take away the fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhe ignoraunce of ſome poore blynde. folkes that folowed hym for none other thynge, but that they thoughte that he woulde fede them bodyly wythout anie more laboure, bicauſe he had nouriſhed them by the multiplication of .v loues,<note place="margin">Iohn .vi. mat. xiiii and .xv.</note> at one tyme, and of .vii. at an other in the deſertes. Other (as it appeareth in the ſame Chapter) eſtemed hym the ſonne of Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph. And by thys contempned hym wythout eſtemmyng any thinge of him but that he was a man, and nothynge of diuinitie they know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged in hym. The whiche onely deitie feedeth and nouriſheth our ſoules and ſpirites. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore bycauſe they ſhoulde not pretende any ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunce, and that they ſhould not excuſe them of ſynne, he ſayed vnto them. I am the lyuyng breade whiche deſcended from heauen. That is to ſaye, from eternitie in temporalitie, by the onely mercy of my father wythout merite of any creature, He ſayed then. I am the lyuyng breade that is deſcended from heauen, as if o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly he had ſayed, deſpiſe me outwarde aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche as you wyll, yet am I other then ye wene, ye ſe the bodie wythout that ye do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe, but in the ſame abideth the plenitude of diuinitie.</p>
            <p>☞ Therefore it foloweth, the breade that I ſhal gyue for the lyfe of the worlde, is my fleſh. The whiche he hath greatly accompliſhed by his death.<note place="margin">Collo. ii.</note> In the whiche for to quycken vs, he hath wyllyngly gyuen hym ſelfe in perfite ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, offerynge hym ſelfe by great obedience wyth a brennynge loue to his father for oure redemption. And ryght proprely he calleth his fleſhe breade,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hon .v.</note> heauenly bread and lyuyng bread bicauſe that he &amp; his father be one ſelfe thinge.
<pb facs="tcp:3923:18"/>In the whiche ſignification, the holy Apoſtle calleth Ieſu Chriſt an heauenly man, or other wyſe he ſhoulde not be oure lyfe and noury ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge.<note place="margin">ii. Cor. xv</note> And in lykewiſe as the bread is not made for it ſelfe, but for the nouryſhynge of other, ſo Ieſus Chriſte the verie ſonne of God is made man for our redemption and lyfe, as it is ſayed. Uerbum caro factum eſt, that is to ſaye, the worde became fleſhe. Yea if that by liuely fayth,<note place="margin">Ihon .i.</note> and aſſured and ſtedfaſt confide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce we be vnited and knit to hym. Then the verie true intelligence and ryghte certeintie of thys chapter is nothinge of the corporal and carnal eating, but of the ſpiritual co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meſtion or eating that is made by a lyuely, entier &amp; ſtedfaſt fayth which vniteh, encorporateh and kniteth vs to Ieſus Chriſte, whiche cauſeth vs to taſte his holy worde, as him ſelfe declareth in the ſayed place, where as he ſayeth. The wordes that I ſpeake ben ſpirite and lyfe, the fleſhe profiteth nothinge, that is to wytte, carnall thoughtes haue no place here about, neither is the fleſhe eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſwalowed into the bealy or ſtomake. But it hath profited much faſtened on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe and to the Lorde offered and ſacrified. For tru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly the fleſhe eaten profiteth not the ſoule, and to ſaye that it were the feadynge of the body,<note place="margin">Iohn .vi. Mens ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſci corpor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eneſcit.</note> it were to merily ſpoken. And it behoueth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily for to vnderſtande thys chapter, as it is aboue ſayed, yea if it pleaſe not the aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ries to make Ieſus Chriſt a lyer for to defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de their fantaſy. The which by the ſame chapter is lightly and ſpedely ſhewed, if it pleaſe you to conſider it well.</p>
            <p>☞ In a certayn text he ſayd thus. Who ſo euer beleueth in me hath eternall lyfe, &amp; I ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:3923:19"/>rayſe hym vp agayne at the laſt daye. In the other texte he ſayeth. Who ſo eateth my fleſhe and drynketh my bloude hath euerlaſtyng lyfe,<note place="margin">Iohn .vi.</note> and I ſhall reyſe hym vp agayne at the laſte day, wherin it is manifeſtly ſene that by theſe two textes, all is one thing of the fayth and of thys eatyng, and who that beleueth in Ieſu Chriſt, eateth and drinketh the body and bloud of Ieſu Chriſte. Or elles the firſte prepoſition (That is to witte, that who ſoeuer beleueth in Ieſus Chriſt hath the lyfe euerlaſtyng) ſhould be falſifyed by thys (thyrd) that foloweth. Ue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely, verely I ſay vnto you, if ye eat not the fleſhe of the ſonne of man, and drynke not his bloud ye ſhall not haue the lyfe in you, howbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it afore he affirmeth that who ſo euer beleueth in hym hath euerlaſtynge lyfe. Whereby it fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth infallibly, that to eate the fleſh, and to drynke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloude of Ieſus Chryſte,<note place="margin">Nota ☞</note> to come to hym and beleue in him is one ſelfe thinge, and there is no man liuyng how ſubtyl that he be (if he be not all oute of hys wyte) that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaye agaynſte it and that it is not true. How many thouſandes of chyldren, yonge adoleſcentes and other perſones haue be and ſhalbe in euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtyng lyfe, that neuer bodyly did eate of thys viſible bread, nor drynke of the Chalyce, and euermore the proceſſe is general, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſayth verely I ſaye vnto you, if ye eate not of the fleſhe of the ſonne of man, &amp; drynke not hys bloude, ye ſhall not haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyfe in you. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is neceſſarye to take and vnderſtande thys texte,<note place="margin">Non ſic <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>duct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> intiqui.</note> not of the viſible and outwarde ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge, but of the inu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ble eatynge, whiche is the inwarde fayth.</p>
            <p>☞ Saynt Auſtine vnderſtode this wel wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:3923:19"/>in the perſone of Ieſus Chriſte and of the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes he wrote thus. Illi putaba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t erogaturu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſe corpus ſuum. Ille dixit aſcenſuru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in celu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">De co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ii. cap. prie antiqui de hereſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> vti<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> integrum. Cum videritis filiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hominis aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentem vbi erat prius certe vel tunc intellige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis quia non eo modo quo putatis erogat cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus ſuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vel tunc intelligetis quia gratia eius non conſumitur morſibus. Item donec finia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ſeculum ſurſum dominus eſt, ſed tamen hic nobiſcum eſt veritas domini. Corpus enim in quo reſurrexit in vno loco eſſe oportet, veritas autem eius vbi<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> diffuſa eſt. That is to ſaye. The Iewes thought that Ieſus Chriſt wolde haue gyuen them his bodye for to eate, and he anſwered the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that he woulde aſcende into hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen whole and perfite, bycauſe they ſhoulde knowe and vnderſtande that they ſhoulde not receyue it in ſuche maner as they thoughte for hys grace conſumeth not by morſelles. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer v<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nto the ende of the worlde the Lorde is aboue. But the truth of the Lorde remayneth here belowe wyth vs. For it behoueth that the bodye of the Lorde whyche is ryſen be in one place. But the truth of the Lorde ſpreadeth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all.</p>
            <p>☞ Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Fulge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tius ſpeakyng of Ieſus Chriſt wrytteth thus.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſgentis u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ad Thraſnti liber .ii.</note> Abſens erat in celo ſecundum humanam ſubſtantiam cum eſſet in terra, et de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relinquens terram quum aſcendiſſet in celum. Secundum vero diuinam et immenſam ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiam nec celum dimittens quum de celo deſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cendit, nec terram deſerens quum ad celu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſ ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. That is to ſaye. Chriſte by his humayne ſubſtaunce was abſente from heauen whan he was in erth, and was leauynge the erth whan he aſcended to heauen. But by hys diuine and
<pb facs="tcp:3923:20"/>infinite ſubſtaunce he lefte not heauen, whan he deſcended from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor alſo lefte not the earth whan he aſcended to heauen.</p>
            <p>☞ I haue alleged theſe two au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t doctours not for to gyue authoritie, or by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to approue the trueth of the Goſpell (for the vertue and power of the worde of God dependeth not of any creature, neyther in heauen nor in earthe, &amp; if al the worlde were againſte it, it remaineth true euerlaſtingly. (But I haue onely broghte them to ſhew y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, that whych is ſayde before is no newe thynge, as theſe falſe Antichryſtes gyue to witte, that alledge theyr lyes, dreames, and fantaſyes, ſettynge aſyde aſmuche as in them is poſſible the holy word of God by theyr gloſes and traditions, by theyr diſtinctions lunatike inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tions. After the which worde of God notwythſtandynge (wyll they or not) all the Popiſhe ordre ſhalbe iudged afore God.</p>
            <p>Wherby entyerly to the ſame I do holde and ſtey me, caſtynge of all that is ſayde by men. in that whyche concerneth diuine thynges wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out euident and true authoritie of ſcripture af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter the whyche all Chriſten men oughte to be readye to gyue anſwere,<note place="margin">Duid h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c dicent fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crifici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> i. Pe. iti.</note> and to ſatiſfie to all men that aſke them a reaſone of the hope, whyche is in them. Than ſythe it is certayne that Ieſus Chriſte, as touchynge the bodye is in heauen liuinge and reignynge, as ſaynt Peter witneſſethe ſaiynge. It behoueth cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynly that heauen receyue him vnto the tyme of reſtoringe of all thynges, that God hathe ſpoken by the mouthe of all hys Prophetes in the times paſt.<note place="margin">Acta. iii.</note> We ought not to ſeeke him bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily in anye other place vnto the tyme that he ſhewe hym ſelfe openly. Who that wyll not
<pb facs="tcp:3923:20"/>forſake all veritie of ſcripture, oughte to lifte vp his herte vnto heauen with all his vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge and mynde, abidynge in humble de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, the houre that it ſhall pleaſe him to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer vs in his reſte. Not worſhippinge here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe any viſible thynge, for the ſcripture ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth vs otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>☞ Alſo Ieſus Chriſt in ordeynynge his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſupper, and the Sacramentall breade to his diſciples ſayde ſimply, Accipite, et manducate, that is to ſaye, take and eate, and ſayde not. Reſpicite, adorate, that is beholde &amp; worſhyp. Nor neuer any of the Apoſtles inticed or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked any to ſuche wroſhyppynge as the prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes of idolles haue done From whoſe tiranny it may pleaſe the Lord God in his ſtrong hand to deliuer his pore people. So he it.<note place="margin">Math. xv.</note>
            </p>
            <p>☞ And if againe (notwithſtanding the thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges afore ſayde) ſtubbornly they do reply theſe wordes of Ieſus Chriſt. Hoc eſt corpus meum that is to ſay, this is my body, to be true, to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I anſwere, that there is nothinge more true, ſo that it be wel vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of vs, for it ſuffiſeth not to allege textes of holy ſcripture, but if thei be wel applied to the true knoledge of the holy goſte wel expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded and tried. Or els Satan a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſt ſhoulde triumph,<note place="margin">Math. iiii.</note> yea &amp; falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, heritikes &amp; ſuch folke as be agaynſt the churche of God woulde beare him awaye.</p>
            <p>☞ In co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion of this mater it reiteth that euery one be wel aduertiſed, that al that which we haue ſayed in thys party, is onely for to gainſaye their ignoraunces, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do maynteine ſo fat &amp; groſſe an aſſiſtence, &amp; bodily preſence of Ieſus Chriſte in the Sacrament with ſuche a multiplication, as they ſaye. For it is not to
<pb facs="tcp:3923:21"/>be doubted that Ieſus Chriſt aſſiſteth not vs at hys holy ſupper, but certaynly by a maner vnſpeakeable &amp; vnable to be told, and vnto vs for the tyme inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſible. Of the which aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce he by his grace make vs partakers. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="declaration">
            <head>¶ The fourth declaration to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande what the Maſſe is.</head>
            <p>THinke ye not my deare brethren that in ſpeaking againſt the Maſſe, I do ſpeake againſt the ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriiſt or the inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſupper. But to the contrary it is for to yelde &amp; reſtore it into the puritie, whiche Ieſus Chriſte by his goodnes hath ordeyned and inſtituted it. For truely there is nothyng ſayd nor done in the maſſe but it is contrary to Ieſus Chriſte &amp; hys worde, the which lightly is to be knowen by this declaration.</p>
            <p>☞ Fyrſt this worde maſſe is a new terme to ſpeake, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which holy ſcriptures neuer made me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion. The whyche terme ſignifieth all that which is ſaid &amp; done in the ſame fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge vnto the ende, compryſynge cerimonies, inclinations, ſonges, ryngynges melodies, ſenſynges, lyghtes, waſhynges, the introyte, the confiteor, the kyrye, the gloria, the oration, one or many, the epiſtle, the gradual, the proſe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leluya, the goſpel, the crede great and lytel, the per omnia, the canon, the ſanctus, the paterno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, the agnus, the poſt communion, the requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, or ita miſſa eſt, Yea &amp; a maſſe is ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pnal or hye, or els low or drye, one vniuerſall &amp; foral folke, another perticuler, and for the fraterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of patronage onely, one for the ryche, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in is mooſte ryngynge, another for the poore
<pb facs="tcp:3923:21"/>wherein is leaſt ryngynge, one of the daye, an other at pleaſure, of the trinitie, of the holye goſte, of the .v. wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, of the croune of thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, of S Fraunces, of ſaynt Auſtine, of S. William, of S. George, of S Roberte and a million of ſuche ſortes, One for the tyme, an other for the goodes. One to go a viage, an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to come againe, one for beaſtes, of. ſ. Hub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert for dogs of ſaynte Antony for ſwine and hogges, of ſaynte Loy for horſes. &amp;c. One for the lyuynge, another for the dead, one for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage another for other fortunes. One of Gau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deamus, another of Requiem, one De ventre, another de teribilibꝰ &amp;c.<note place="margin">Not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gettynge the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge maſſe.</note> And after as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe is, ſuch veſtimentes is aſſigned. As louers and plaieres deuiſe by coloures. That is to wytte, yelowe for the apoſtles, Reade for the martirs Grene for the confeſſors, whit for the virgins Blacke for the dead or the ſoules, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently of other. It is a dreame to thynke thereof-</p>
            <p>☞ Now it is ſo manifeſte that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very blind folkes maye ſe that of theſe thynges a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayde. Ieſus Chriſte neuer ſpake, and of it all ordeyned nothynge. Wherfore to caſte awaye theſe fantaſyes of men, is not caſtyng awaye of that whyche Ieſus Chriſte hath inſtituted.</p>
            <p>And if any make obieccion that ther be good thynges in the maſſe at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſte as is the epiſtle the Goſpell &amp; the Crede, the Pater noſter, and other lyke and oughte not thus to be diſpiſed. To that I anſwer that it ſuffiſeth not to haue good thinges, but they oughte to be well vſed, and they muſt be applyed as they ought to be. Alſo enchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tours nicromancers and wytches that in their noughtines vſeth ſome good wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des
<pb facs="tcp:3923:22"/>ſhal they be excuſed of crime, which awyſe man would not ſaye. And like wiſe bi y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame purpoſe maie be ſaid to excuſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe becauſe of the good wordes ſaide therin, which great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is abuſed and done otherwyſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the word of God ſupporteth And that it is ſo, it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth clerely, whan Ieſus Chriſte preached de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared and ſhewed furth, the Goſpell and hys holy worde to euerye creature. Not for to crye or ſinge it.<note place="margin">Mat. xvi.</note> And yet theſe poore ſacrifiers do no thinge ſaufe onely they reade or ſinge a certain collet. Yea, and in a ſpeache whiche the people (and them ſelfe, for the moſte parte) do not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand. Albeit that ſainte Paul in the power of God commaundeth that we ſhall not ſpeak in the churche,<note place="margin">1. Co. xiiii</note> that is to ſaye, in the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of the faithfull, but onely in a ſpeche that euery one maye vnderſtande, or at the leafte af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terwarde for to bee expounded and declared.</p>
            <p>For what auailed it (although we ſaye good thinges) and ſpeake French, Dutch or Italiſh in the preſence of them that vnderſtandeth it not? and ſo it is to ſynge, rede or ſaye the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell in Latyne or other wordes of God and is not vnderſtand. What edifiyng cometh threof what inſtruction? or what doctrine of helth is to the ſimple people?</p>
            <p>☞ Iuge now I praye you, ſyth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt of the maſſe (as thei do vſe it) is nought worth what than is the reſidue? Truly it is a let of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion a deſtruction and ruyne of all goodnes, ſo fearfull (to them that know it) that neuer was none ſuch lyke as I do declare it. S Paul ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the goſpel is the power of ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to all beleuers,<note place="margin">Rom. i</note> but he ſayth not that for ſyngyng of the goſpell, to crie it, to howle it, or bere it in a
<pb facs="tcp:3923:22"/>golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> boke or ſiluer before the ſtomacke, or in a towell hanginge aboute the necke (as many fooles eſteme) but he meneth the Goſpell to be ſhewed, preached, declared, and receyued in the vertue and power of the ſpirite of God.<note place="margin">Domo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> do audie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te.</note> For aſmuche as fayth (wythout the whyche none maye be ſaued) cometh of heringe.</p>
            <p>☞ And what thinge was there euer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hathe put a ſide the euanglycal preachinge ſomuche as thys proud maſſe? Yf S. Paule came for to preache in the maſſe tyme, God knoweth how he ſhoulde be receyued. Likewiſe if a pardoner or a berer of Relykes, or anye other tryfler ſhoulde come, yet they wyll ſaye to him, Make haſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> office is longe, and neuerrtheles they be agreed.</p>
            <p>☞ What thinke ye that they woulde do to a ſimple chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that would gainſaye their abuſe O Lord God, where is the tyme that thi ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te Paule continued and prolonged hys ſermon tyll midnight?<note place="margin">Act. xx.</note> And ſyth we be in thys purpoſe that we are, ſeing that the Pope doth paynt hym ſelfe ſo well wyth the name of S. Peter and S. Paul for to mainteine his tiran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny, where is the maſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both ſaide? We rede in the Actes of the Apoſtles how S. Paule went from towne to towne,<note place="margin">ii. Cor. xi</note> from one rigio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to another, in Aſie, Affryke, &amp; in Europe to thentente to exalte, preach, and ſhewe furth the name of Ieſus Chriſt, trauaylynge by land and ſea vnto the death for him. And how he diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>puted and confounded hys gainſayers. But of the maſſe there is no mencion made but onely of brekynge of breade, and of the holy ſupper of Ieſus Chriſt, the which by the maſſe is holi abolyſhed and ſet a ſyde. O miſerable abuſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:3923:23"/>
            <head>¶ The .v. declaracion is of ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry frutes that come of the Maſſe.</head>
            <p>IT is wryten that an yl tre can bere no good fruite wherby after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knoledge of ſo much euill that thys vnhappy maſſe bryngeth to vs,<note place="margin">Mat. vii.</note> what frut maye ye now know therby? but errour hypocryſi, ydolatry, tro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pery, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giling ſeduction, ſtrife, blaſphemy, maledictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and abhomynacion. To be ſhorte, it is a totall dampnacion and perdicion. And this I ſpeake touchynge the ſecrete and hid thinges. But as to the viſible thinges of the world &amp; the fleſhe, that euermore bendeth to a bothenles pytte of euyll,<note place="margin">Operemi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tti non ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um qui perit.</note> I ſhall declare ſomwhat.</p>
            <p>It is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munly ſaid that al thynges be made for the life and ſo they ſaye, of whom Saynte Paul ſpeaketh, that their beli is there God, the which bely is a terible God,<note place="margin">Iohn .vi. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i. iii.</note> where to without ſeſſyng muche is offered, muche preſented and ſacrified notwithſtandinge that it tourneth al to corruption, and that it neuer gyueth reſt to theſe myſerable ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes that ſettyth al their care to ſatiſfie, fat, and pleaſe it, as ſleuthful, lykerous, dronkers, kermorauntes, fat calues fat bulles, and ſuch maner of ſwine.</p>
            <p>☞ Now was ther neuer ſuch an inuention founde ſo ſubtilly as to lyue without takinge payne wythoute laboure or thoughte the ket<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge well furniſhed for to make fat ſoppes and to fede their fat trippes Thys is I enſure you a plentious maſſe that bryngeth furth ſo much dedly fruyte, vnder apparence of holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes wherwyth the poore worlde is ſwallowed vp and deuoured. Thincke (I praye you) how much fruite brinketh in theyr finger kiſſynges
<pb facs="tcp:3923:23"/>that they name the offertory of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe. Theſe byg lubbers take no thoughte for all the weke to fede theyr ribawdrye. Alas for pite,<note place="margin">Corbam. Corbam. Corbam. Mor. vii.</note> how ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny poore women bereth to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that wherwyth they ſhoulde fede theyr children, or helpe the poore nedy? And in dede thys maner of offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring came of the fyrſt church of Ieſus Chriſt. Where as the faithful brought of theyr godes and gaue them to the Deacon that was ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ☜ a ſeruaunt to the poore to diſtribute to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that whyche was geuen to hym. But theſe fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes take all and kepe all, wherein they be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen theues, for they kepe to them ſelues the goodes of the poore, to fede and maynteyne theyr fylthynes and fat belles. Thys is the fyrſte fruyte.</p>
            <p>☞ Another frute much lyke to this, this ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyful maſſe bringeth furth, by the whiche theſe worſhipfull maſſemongers haue gadered and heaped, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder the ſhadow of longe pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers they haue rauiſhed an deuoured the houſes of the poore wydowes and orphans.<note place="margin">mat. xxi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> The whiche princypally was made for foundacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of anniuerſaries yeres mindes and yerely and dayly maſſes. By the whiche falſe and outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious meanes they haue obteyned and heapyd vp riches vnpoſſible to be thought, as houſing rentes, lyuelodes poſſeſſions, Lordſhips,<note place="margin">Iam ſec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria ad ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicem ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boris poſt ta eſt.</note> tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, caſtels, contries, barounies, duckedomes and that moreouer realmes, and principalytes. Here is a ſhrewed tree in the earth ouerplanted and roted, the whyche neuertheles ſhalbe cut downe and deſtroyed by the ſwerde of God.</p>
            <p>☞ And from this merueilous, earthly and ſo riche fruyte is another ſpronge.<note place="margin">Mat. ii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> That is that theſe ſhorne maſſemongers, that at the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng
<pb facs="tcp:3923:24"/>were poorer than coblers, haue made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to be called mayſters and lordes, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue al other haue occupied,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u. xi</note> optayned, and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped in eueri place the firſt ſeates. Than ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me thei into libertie (not of ſpirite) but of the fleſh, redy and licenſed to al euyll. And moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, they haue exe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted, withdrawne, and ſepa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rated them ſelues from the obedience, whyche by the commaundement of God, thei oughte &amp; owe (will they or not) to Princes and lordes. For ſ. Paul writeth thus. Omnis anima pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatibus ſuperemine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tibus ſubdita ſit.<note place="margin">Ro. xiiii</note> That is to ſay, euery ſoule be ſubiect to the hie powers But the holy Apoſtle ſayd not. Omnis anima laica, that is to ſay: euerye lay mans ſoule, but eueri ſoul. As it was once anſwred in a college of Paris by a maſter Aſſe, whoſe noſethrels &amp; fete ought to haue bene cloue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſent to paſture</p>
            <p>Out of all this ſpronge another fruite more pleaſaunt, agreable, and dilicious to the tendre and dilicate gentilmen. That is, that by one accord (yea, by a commune lawe, made among them ſelues) they ſhould lyue in mery wanton nes and lecherous idelnes, without laboure or trauaile. For their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des be to ſoft, but to plai at tennes, boules, tables, cardes, and dyce, to leape and daunce for theyr paſtime, but for to labour, fye, becauſe they be anoynted, greaſed, and their pates plucked. And al this, ſolatious goodnes commeth of this ioly maſſe. O maſſe maſſe, howe gentle art thou, howe louyng and pleaſaunte to theſe folke. Howe can they hate the? howe can they leaue the? howe can the ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyſh the, ſyth thou haſte ſet them in ſuch an ea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſy quiete and reſt, to labour nothyng at al. And that mor is, if they can reade or ſynge a maſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:3923:24"/>lifte vp theyr armes and knele, haueyng a por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſe to bable theyr mattens, they nede none other thynge. As for bokes, volumes, and quai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers of holy ſcripture to ſearch and ſtudy, it for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth not: for they he not requiſit for the maſſe.</p>
            <p>☞ And as for ſtudy, it is a melancholious bu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſines, werines and a noyous, not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient for ſuch ydle beaſtes, that wold lyue wythout any thought and by the ſweat af other mens faces. Oh howe contrary is S. Paule to them? The which not wythſtandyng that he was an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of Ieſus Chriſt, a Biſhop, but not mytred, nor horned, a Doctour of veritie, a doctour of the church but not hooded, nerthells he wroght wyth hys handes, and for to do ſo he admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth and deſyreth euery perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but what haue they to do wyth God or ſaynt Paule?</p>
            <p>☞ Yet an other fruite of this maſſe, and tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a great euyl I wyl ſhewe as nowe. The fruite is greate and encreaſed, for neuer henne layed ſo many egges, and hatched ſo many chyckens as this maſſe hathe brought vs ſhorne poules.</p>
            <p>And what man can thincke the nombre of the cockerelles that runne after harlottes, as cockes after hennes. And whan theſe iolye lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers haue layd their layghters, and ſitten their brodes, thei ſit in their temples, ſinging as coc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes on their perches, yea (&amp; properlier to ſay) de ſkant in counterfeit thinges, gapyng, criyng, &amp; howlyng. So many cockes, cockrels, &amp; pullets, that is to ſay, of Monkes, Friers, Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, laiſiſters, this fat maſſe hatched, &amp; fed, that it is wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der to beleue, and to ſatiſfie ſo great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nombre, it was of force neceſſary to bild many henhouſes &amp; neſtes, to lodge ſo many lapwyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre if ye can al the cloiſters, abbai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, priories, monaſteries, temples, chanonries, prebendes, alters, portatifs, &amp; not portat ifs, and
<pb facs="tcp:3923:25"/>ſuch other thinges that the maſſe hath brought furth. And vpon that, thinke a litel I praie you and ye ſhall perceiue what it ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye be, is it not wel multiplyed. Auarice hath wroghte a paſe, as wytneſſeth one of theyr order named Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam de Peraldo, in his tyme biſhop of Lyons in the ſome y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath made of vertues &amp; vices,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> de P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at do.</note> in the ſeconde parte, in the title of Simony. Where as he ſayeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> auarice hath found the multitude of al tars &amp; the colectes of the maſſe the whych thing finalli is tourned into horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble idolatry For by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meanes the pore people haue be lerned to ſeke &amp; worſhip god, in te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples &amp; places made w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s hand. Albeit (as Eſaye ſaith &amp; S. Stepha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> allegeth) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the moſt higheſt is not habitau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in the maner as they wene for,<note place="margin">Eſai. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Bi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eta. vii.</note> the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> liuing god is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hert ſoule &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithful. For the whiche cauſe Ieſus Chriſt ſaid, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the true worſhipers worſhipped not the Lorde God ueyther in the mountayne nor in Ieruſalem,<note place="margin">Iohn .iiii.</note> but in ſpirite and truth, And therfore faith Saint Paule, that the faithfull is the habitation and temples of the holy goſt. And alſo Ieſus Chriſte, wyllynge to geue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolacion to all faythfull people, in ſpeakynge of hys father, of him ſelfe and of the ſpirite of verite, which the world can not compriſe ſayd thus. We ſhall come to hym, and make oure dwelling wyth hym, he ſayd not, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhoulde come into a te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, or in ſuch a place, or in ſuche an aultar.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. vi. vi. Cor. vi.</note> But he ſayd, we ſhould come to him and make our dwelling w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him. Wherfore tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by your aduiſe hath the people thus be taught to renne hither and thyder,<note place="margin">Ioh. xiiii.</note> but for to catche ſuch as they bringe? O inſaciable coueytouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, Lertaynly I dare wel ſaye, that the bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bats
<pb facs="tcp:3923:25"/>or watchinge theues lurkinge in wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, be not to be dreade as theſe Antichriſtes, the whiche haue not alonly pylled &amp; robbed the temporall goodes fro the people but haue caſte out, and by thyr falſe doctrine almooſte al the world out of the waye of ſaluacion, and ſtrei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it from the Lorde God and from all verite. Hereabout we ought not to ſpeake, but onely he wayle, ſob and weepe by greate dolour &amp; he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines. And therefore I leaue to ſpeake of their falſe miracles, of their idols of Golde, Siluer ſtone, earth and of woode. &amp;c. Of their pilgry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages theyr viages, and ſuch maners deceites whereby the worlde is brought in to a darke botomles pyt</p>
            <p>☞ This is the euil that at the beginninge of thys vngracious fruyte I was in purpoſe to ſpeake, that of all euills it is the greateſte, and neuer man coulde imagine worſſe. And what would ye worſſe then to begiuen into reproued ſences. To be ſtriken with ſo greate darkenes, that they do come and iudge the good to be ill,<note place="margin">Be qui di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t Sonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> and the ill to be good. All thys by thys maſſe is come on the people as ye maye clerely vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande by this that is declared aboue.<note place="margin">Eſaie .v.</note>
            </p>
            <p>☞ Of thys euil aboue all other the Prophet tes haue made mencion whan by greate threte ninges of the euyll that was to come ouer the miſbeleuinge people,<note place="margin">Eſaie .vii. Mat. xiii. Mar. iiii. Luc. viii. Ioha. xii. Ac. xxviii Rom. xi. Pſ. Lviii.</note> haue aforeſpoken y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blind<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes and curſednes therof. And is it reaſon that be wyll not take and receyue bliſſinge, that cur ſinge come to hym? Wherevpon it nedeth not to pretende or allege ignoraunce, ſaing, if there be any euill it is onely for them that hath inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it, truely alſo for them that foloweth it. As it is writen. Yf one blinde man lede another,<note place="margin">Mat. xv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <pb facs="tcp:3923:26"/>both of them falleth in the diche. And therfore I praye euery one to be ware.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="declaration">
            <head>¶ The .vi. declaracion is of the cauſe and wherefore the maſſe ought to be maynteined.</head>
            <p>THe cauſe is euidente, ſith it bringeth furth ſo muche fruyte. Is it not a ſpring of fat ſoppes and brothe? Is it not a good milche cowe, and who ſawe euer ſuche a ſowe that ſo eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſo ſwetely, &amp; ſo fatly hath ſo many pygges? where fore ſhoulde they leaue it ſith they finde it ſo good Truely with good righte they main teyne it. For it is very handſome for the bely, They haue no nede to do any thinge, &amp; leſſe for to ſtudy.<note place="margin">Da. xiii.</note> What wyll ye more? Other cauſe I fynde not wherfore it oughte to be mainteined but if it be lyke the ſacrifiers of Babilon that mainteined theyr God Bell, bicauſe they were nouriſhed, their wifes and ſmall children, with that which was offered to the ſayde idoll.<note place="margin">Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dutiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> di ſtruyiſſe</note> But as one Daniell chaunced thider that deſtroied theyr falſe workes, and ſo were confoundded. God ſhall ariſe, and all redie he hath reiſed a Daniel ful of the ſpirite of verite, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhal plain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly at the full gyue knowlege of the falſenes of the maſſe, ſo couered and cloſed, and there ſhal our poore ſacrifiers be ouerthrowen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="declaration">
            <head>¶ The. vii declaracion is of the meanes, of the maner, and howe this poore maſſe maye be mainteined.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:3923:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SYth that for the cauſes afore ſayde the maſſe ought to be mainteined, there reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth but the maner, the meane, and howe that maye be done, for it is the chyefe of their matter. Attende here poore ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, for ye haue no more any other refuge or ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And therfore ye ought to loue me wel, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge that I am ſo thoughtful of your b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſines Herken than wel, &amp; reteine the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel that fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, for ye can neuer find a better for your matter. Now ye muſt note how many waies a thyng may be mainteyned.</p>
            <p>☞ Firſt alledginge auncient cuſtome. But herein I will proue it noughte worthy. For howebeit y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſith .iiii. or .v. C. yeares your maſſe hath be rieſed, taughte &amp; builded in apes toies and iuglinges which we ſe now, yet was it not in the auncient and firſt churche. And therefore if we muſt allege auncient cuſtom, it is not for you, but a gainſt you euery white. Moreouer in diuine thynges, &amp; that are by the ordinaunce of God, contrarie cuſtome made by men, hath no place. And ought not to be called cuſtome, but abuſe and corrupcion.</p>
            <p>☞ Secondly a thinge is mainteined by plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralite and multitude The whyche thynge maye be doone in humayne thynges onelye, to make an ende &amp; agremente vppon the difference that maye be betwene men. But ſuche a thinge can not be done nor oughte to be done, in thinges ſtabliſhed of God. For truly the verite of God dependeth not of greate nomber of the wyll or fantaſie of men. Whereby all be it that ye alledge greate multytude of folke for your parte, that in thys caſe cannot ſerue you, for it is not to purpoſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3923:27"/>
            <p>☞ Thyrly, by lies, falſe vnderſtandinge, wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, hipocriſy, kepinge good countinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulacion, feyninge ſome very ill thinge: as if it were very good, for to maynteine them ſelfe for a tyme, wherwyth many a monge you, at thys your greate nede can not greatly arme, couer,<note place="margin">Fronti nuſſa fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note> and helpe your ſelfe, but yet truly at the laſt it can not warraunte you, for by proceſſe of tyme a thinge painted or ſteined is diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the wether.</p>
            <p>☞ Fourthly ye ſhal marke and to be ſhorte, that in .ii. other maners a thynge is maynte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p>The one is by force, the other by righ Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore one of theſe thinges ye muſt chuſe, aduiſe you which of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> two is moſt fet or mete for you Yf ye yelde you to the right, truly your maſſe is at an ende.<note place="margin">Super Omaia vincit Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas. iii. Eſd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras, iiii.</note> For falſenes, hipocriſi and lienge dreames, by right and veritie are caſte downe. Than reſteth nomore to yon but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fore, which is not the beſt parte. So wote I not what to do, but that by your wicked ſpirite (as ye haue wel be goune) at the force ye ſhal kepe you, and in aſmuche as ye maye do, ſtope and lette the generall Councelle. By thys meane ye maye mainteine it for a tyme. But the Lorde (againſt whome ye fyghte) wyll deſtroy you at length.</p>
            <p>☞ O Chriſten people conſider by what mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes theſe gallauntes mainteneth theyr buſines is it not all by force? They enpriſon, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroye, they pil, they driue a waye, they baniſhe they burne, they ſlee, they drowne and murdre as many as they maye, as manye as gayne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaye them. By ſhameles lyes alſo, ſuche wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of iniquite (becauſe they dare not abyde
<pb facs="tcp:3923:27"/>the lyghte) diffame all louers of veritie whiche is extreme malyce. To gyue Golde, ſiluer, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels and preſentes to whom they knowe haue power to mayntene them, they be diligent. For theyr onelye hope is all together in men, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in manifeſtly appereth theyr vnexchewing and approching ruine.<note place="margin">Iere. &amp; xvii.</note> For curſed is that man that taketh the fleſhe for his arme and his ſtrength. It is ſayde that all plantes which the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father hath not planted ſhalbe rooted out.<note place="margin">Mat. xv.</note>
            </p>
            <p>That is to vnderſtand aſwel of the wicked, as theyr workes. Moreouer it behoueth vs well to hope that God by hys greate goodnes wyll ſende vs ſome vertuous Ezechias or reiſe a true Ioſias that by highe corrage ſhall ſet and conſtitute an ordre ouer all. Than ſhall we ſe the face of the lord ſhine vpon vs, as the bright Sonne after a derke clowdi wether. For if the holy Sacramente that not onely repreſenteth to vs, but alſo preſenteth vs the precious bodi and worthy bloude of oure redemptour and onely ſauiour Ieſus Chriſte, were kepe in the purenes. Yf the ſaide holy and ſacrate ſupper of Ieſus wherein his ſimplicite, well ſette for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, the vſage of the ſame wel obſerued, the efficacie and fruite therof wel vnderſtand, the death and paſſion of the ſauioure (becauſe we ſhoulde not be vnkynde agayne) taughte at large, the promiſſes pronounced and declared as it oughte to be, the maſſe ſo full of cerimoni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es partetly amended and corrected truly the poore worlde, the whyche by it, is ſo greately troubled &amp; waſted, ſhoulde be in reſte, and from a greate vnhappines, ſhould retourne in to tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quilite and felycite.</p>
            <p>The whyche it maye pleaſe the eternall father
<pb facs="tcp:3923:28"/>to giue vs, for the reuerence and dignite of his onely ſonne moſt beſte beloued his very Chriſt oure Lorde, to whome be perpetuall honoure and glory. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ C. G. to the faythfull reders.</head>
            <p>MOoſte deare brethren and frendes,<note place="margin">i. Pete. i.</note> bought (as ſainte Peter ſayth) not by golde or ſiluer, but wyth the pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cious bloude of Ieſus Chriſte, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer you not to be bought &amp; ſolde, the ſacrifiers vnto this daye haue bought &amp; ſolde vs, and be ye not ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes to men, ſubiecting you to them for to diſpleaſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord God But conſider your liberty &amp; ſpiritual dignite, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with God hath made you fre, and leaue the ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uitude or thraldome of the maſſe and of theſe ſacrifiers, that put you in ouer greate ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, agaynſte the ordinaunce of oure Lorde, as here afore oure faythfull &amp; good frende Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cort, hath full well propoſed and ſhewed, as a true cenſor or Iudge. Wherunto I praye you by the name of Ieſus to thinke diligenly ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and exactely to iudge, as it was afore ſaide to you in the beginnynge, withoute hatred or corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of iudgement. And thou reader prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally whiche haſt the knowlege of theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges. Beholde howe thou maiſte not be excuſed afore God, ſeynge that thou aſſiſteſte to the maſſe, heade of all idolatrye and abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as willynge to communicate and be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of the table of Chriſte, and of Antichriſte, or of the deuill, &amp; by that meanes to ſerue two contrary Lordes, whiche can not be done for it muſte all to the one, or all to the other, not hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge
<pb facs="tcp:3923:28"/>with both the fete, but as Helfe ſayd. Yf the Lorde be God ſerue hym. If Baal be god folowe hym. Yf alſo the ſupper of God is of God, kepe it, if the maſſe be not true leaue it, not waneryng on both ſides, as folke wyth two faces, whereof ſaynte Paull reprouinge the Corinthyans that likewiſe woulde aſſiſte to either of them, ſaide. Ye can not drinke the chalice of oure Lord, and the chalice of deuiles. Ye can not be partakers of the table of oure Lorde, and of the deuils table. Will we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke the Lorde to yre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. &amp;c. And yet aboue all, thou miſerable whiche haſt cleare knowledge of the verite, howe dare thou procure, take and reteyne the benefices, that iuſtly we oughte to call venefices or ſocerys, procedynge of thys foul, vilanous &amp; abominable ſourge of Rome? Thou knoweſte that they be gooddes de an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema or of curſyng more horrible tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that of Hierico, conquired. Thou arte not ignoraunte in receiuynge a Biſhoprycke, abbay, cure, or chanonry, that thou conſenteſt to all the abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which be daily done in the ſayd pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, agaynſt the honour of god what excuſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can thou pretende afore God and before man, ſeyng that thou knoweſt by the worde of God that they be but abuſes? Some wyll ſaie, if I take not this benefice another ſhal haue it that ſhall perſecute the Chriſtians, that ſhall ruffle with the profites therof, and that will giue no thynge to the pore. To that I anſwere thou whited wall, wilifox, painted ſepulchre, and falſe hypocrite, that thou ought not ſo to do in any wiſe. For the Apoſtle ſayth. It behoueth not to do euill,<note place="margin">Rom. iii.</note> to thentent that there may ariſe goodnes thereby. Than what is he that kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth
<pb facs="tcp:3923:29"/>not that richeſſes, cauſeth theyr poſſeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours to be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned, by pride, auarice, glotony, and by lechery, that procedeth of them, as of a foule puddle. Thou than that receiueſt the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices and ſingeſt the maſſe, or at leaſt wayes then co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſenteſt and aſſiſteſt them that ſinge it. Be it for to haue the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modite, or profite, and liuing, ſmalli regarding the goſpel but digging and hidinge the talent of the Lord in the meane while. What ſoeuer Goſpell and verite thou ſaiſte that thou haft, thou arte the leſſe to be ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cuſed. For as a blinde and a leder of the blinde, puttynge offence and ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der afore thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure thou dooſte not committe idolatrie only but cauſeſt the other to do idolatri ſeruing the idoll whan thou ſaiſt by wordes, or doeſt with a pece of dreade and ſayſt, here is the God, thy ſauioure that a gaine bought the,<note place="margin">Ev. vvii Pſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ii. Ro. vii</note> lyke as Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron by ouer greate infirmite and diſobedience wyllynge in thoſe dayes to pleaſe men more then God. And alſo Ieroboam ſtired mor by ambicion and couetiſe, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by ignorance, ſaide to theyr people ſettinge furth a Calfe here is the God O Iſrael that lede the out of the land of Egipt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">iii. Regu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .vii. <hi>8.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ii. Para. liii. a. iiii. Re. xxiii. a. iiii. Reg. xxiii. a. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>u oratis one Mas naffe.</note>☞ Alas mi mooſte beloued conſider in what fearful inconuenience, in what peril and daun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger of perdicion ye be, in ſeinge before youre eyes and communicatinge ſuche horrible blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemes, a gaynſte the maieſty and goodnes of God. Therfore leaue and forſake ſuche ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry cominge out of Babylon, or elles put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>waye euill fro amonge you, reſiſt with power to deſtroye it, as the true miniſter Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and theſe true kinges Aſa, Ioſaphat. Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias. Ezechias, and Manaſſe, But more ſoner
<pb facs="tcp:3923:29"/>by the lyuely and myghty worde of God, euen as it behoueth you to do: albeit that it is enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the Princes and Goueruours to put all ſuch Idolatrie to ruine and confucion, by all meanes that may be. Otherwiſe if ye perſeuer thus, ye ſhall neuer entre into the lande of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, no more than Aaron and hys dyd, but yet that more is to be eſtemed, into the realme of God, the ſpirituall and verye lande of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. Into the which God by hys grace w<hi rend="sup">c</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawyng vs fro thys worldly Egypte lead vs by the great Moyſes &amp; myghty Ioſue, whych is Ieſus Chriſte. Amen.</p>
            <p>☞ But becauſe the better and bryflyer wee may knowe the blacke fro the white, the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes fro the lyght, the dreame fro the veritie: I wyll reherſe in an epiloge a lyttle gatheryng paynted as it were in a table and wyl ſet forth the ſayde, maſſe wyth hys colours, wherin at one ſyght he wholy may bee thought, but not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wythſtandynge more imagined in the herte.</p>
            <p>For in wryttynge of it, and porterrynge it: all quilles and penſelles woulde neuer ſuffice, for the hyghe and infinite abuſes that bee in thys Maſſe and therin conteyned.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ Here folowe certayne damnable ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſes that are in the maſſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarye to the holy ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of Ieſus Chriſt</head>
            <p>FOraſmuche as the ſayde maſſe is but mannes inuention and neuertheles com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunded, as if it wer of God. Agaynſt Deutr. xii. a.d. Mat. xv. b. Rom. xiiii. b.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3923:30"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ☞ That it is in ſuch diſguyſynges and po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes of veſtime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes in diuers facio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and colours to the foloweynge of the Iews and Painims. Agaynſt Luke xx. g.i. Peter .iii. a. ii Timo. ii. c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> ☞ That it is ordeined after ſuch a ſort, that wythout holyed ſtone, that wythout tapers, &amp; ryngynges, it oughte not to be ſayede. Againſt Mathew .xxvi. c. ii. Corh. xi. c.</p>
            <p>☞ That they eſteme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame the more worth for the perſons that ſaye it, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> conſtitute in moſt hygh office and dignitie againſt. ii. Paral. xviii c. Rom. ii. b.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> ☞ Bycauſe they that make oblacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of it, as ſacrifiyng Ieſus Chriſt againe Agaynſte .i. Corh. xi. e.f. Ebru. ix. g.x.c.d.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> ☞ By the ſame promiſeyng ſatiſfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and remiſſion of ſinnes. Agaynſt Eſai .lxiii. d. Ebr. x. c. Actu. iiii. b.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> ☞ Becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue ſo much in the ſame their fals and blaſphemous Cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which the abuſes be theſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ The abuſes of the Canon.</head>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> THe Canon is more eſtemed of them than the Goſpell, for they haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boden all Laie perſons to reade it. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte Galathians .i. b.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ☞ It is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded them to reade it vpon payne of deadely ſinne, agaynſt Deut. v. d. Prouerb. x: a.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> ☞ They make oblacion of breade and wyne agaynſt Ebru .ix. c. d i Peter .i. d.</p>
            <p>☞ Thei offer the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne to the father, that hath offerred hym ſelfe. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Agaynſt .i. Timoth. ii. b. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre. i. a.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3923:30"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> ☞ They praie that theyr ſacrifice may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted as the ſacrifice of Abell and of Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agaynſt. Ebre .xii. f.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> ☞ They eſteme as the Capernaites to eate Chriſte in fleſhe and bones within the breade. agaynſt, Iohan, vi. a.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>After the Canon.</head>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> ☞ In the ſame thei deny the article of the aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cencion of Chriſte. Agaynſte. Luke .xxiiii. g. Act .i. b.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> ☞ The prieſte alone breaketh and eateth the breade. Agaynſte. Luke .xii. b .i. Cor .xi. b.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> ☞ Of that ſuperſticiouſly they make three partes of the hoſte. Agaynſte. Math .xxvi. c. i. Corin .xi. f.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> ☞ Of that it is ſayd onely in the mornyng, and faſting, againſt. Mat .xxvi. c. Iohan .xiii. a</p>
            <p>☞ Of that it is deffended that none be ſo bolde as to tuch the breade and the chalice that the prieſt toucheth, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n=".12"/> againſt Luke .xxii. b.</p>
            <p>☞ The death of Chriſt is not auanced therin agaynſte .i. Corin .ix. e.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/>
            </p>
            <p>They do the maſſe in commemoration of ſain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> Agaynſte Luke .xxii.i. Corin .xi.</p>
            <p>☞ It is ſayde for the dead. Contrary to the ſupper ordeyned for them alyue. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> Agaynſt. Mat xxvi. e .i. Corin .xi. e.</p>
            <p>☞ They lifte vp the breade and the chalice that it maye be worſhipped. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> Agaynſte Erodi. xx. a.</p>
            <p>☞ For the ieſtures and cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that they make like hypocrites, mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mers &amp; iuglers, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be laughed at. Agaynſt the Ephe .v. a.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> ☞ Bicauſe that oftentimes the ſacrifier is
<pb facs="tcp:3923:31"/>a fornicatour, whoſe maſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended to be herde, howbeit it is herde, againſt i. Corin .v. c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/> ☞ Of that one is conſtreined to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate wyth the fornicator, howbeit we ought not to eate wyth hym .i. Corin .v. c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> ☞ For that thei co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ferme and ſauour another purgatory than the bloude of Ieſus Chriſte that cleanſeth vs. Agaynſte .i. Iohan .i. He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre .i. a.</p>
            <p>☞ For that they celebrate as Simoniakes for ſiluer and other temporall thinges agaynſt theyr inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Agaynſt. Mat .x, a. Act .viii. c.</p>
            <p>☞ Bycauſe, it is applied and ſayde aſwell for beaſtes and thinges that be loſte, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> as for the people, as willyng to heale al ſores wyth one plaiſter, agaynſte .i. Cor .ii.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/> ☞ In that one is ſolempne, and hath many ceremonyes, and maners of dignytes more than the other, agaynſt. Math.xxvi. c. Cor .xi. e.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="24"/> 
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> In that the ſynger of the maſſe is called more worthy, &amp; to haue more authoritie than al the aungelles, than the virgin Mary and ſain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. agaynſt, Roma .ii. b. Ephe .vi. c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="25"/> 
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> In that, that by the vertue of the wordes they eſteme that Ieſus Chriſte deſcendeth bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily into the hoſte, wyth all the court of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. agaynſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="26"/> Luk .xxiiii. g. Act .iiii d</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> By that in ſo greate ſuperſticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they kepe theyr hooſties, ſubiectes to rotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, in boxes and awineries, bearing them at certayne times and daies thorow the ſtretes againſt. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="27"/> Math .xxvi. c. Cor .xi. e.</p>
            <p>☞ In that they retourne home as foliſhely with the ſame, as they wente out therwith, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt. Cor .xiiii. c.d. Col .iii. c,</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3923:31"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="28"/> ☞ In that the ſacrifier ſpeaketh in ſecrete, ouer the breade and ouer the wine, openly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the inſtitution of Ieſus Chriſte. For it is euident and certayne that our Lord ſpake not to the bread, nor to the wine whan he ſayd take, eate, this is my body. &amp;c. But he ſpake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that were there aſſiſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Mat .xxvi</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="29"/> ☞ In that they ſay &amp; make the maſſe in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>memoration of aungels, and ſayntes, direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt the intention of Ieſus Chriſte that ſayd. Hoc facite in commemorationem meam, that is to ſay, do ye this in the remembraunce of me.</p>
            <p>☞ In that by theyr ouer greate boldnes and pride, or rather curſed ſacrilege, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> they giue to the people but the one halfe of the ſacramente, as if they were but halfe. Chriſten folke, or that Ieſus Chriſte was not ſo wiſe as they be whan he ſayde. Bibite exco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>omnes, that is to ſay, drinke of it euery one. And of thys mater ſaynte Paule writynge to the Corinthians, wrote not onely for the ſacrifiers, but for all the people .i. Corint .xi.</p>
            <p>YE ſhal knowe many other obuſions of the maſſein the boke called the Caute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les or wiles of the maſſe. Certaynly ful of cauteles, in the diuine rationall with oute reaſon and nothinge leſſe than di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine, in the ſome Angelyke, more than inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine and deuily ſhe. In the paſtorall the ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les fede and nouryſhe wyth thiſtles, and at the brydge of all euil wherwyth they be al pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call wholly filled.</p>
            <list>
               <head>¶ Theſe be ſondry fruytes of the maſſe that be mooſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune and notable.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:3923:32"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>1</hi> MVltitude of prebendes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> Multitude of prieſtes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> Multitude of temples &amp; chapels.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4</hi> Multitude of aultars.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5</hi> Diuers oblations and offringes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6</hi> Worldly riches and pryde.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7</hi> Idleneſſe and trwandiſſe of the ſhauen.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8</hi> Multitude of harlotes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9</hi> Fained houres and prayers.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10</hi> Deteſtable hypocriſy.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11</hi> Deuourynge of widowes, orphans, &amp; the poore.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12</hi> Renounſyng and deſtructyng of the death and paſſion of Chriſte.</item>
            </list>
            <p>¶ And ſo conſequently of the other, whyche are infinite.</p>
            <p>TO make ſhort y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> errour of the maſſe is moſte deadly &amp; hurtfull, aſwell to the goodes as to the perſones, in as much as it ſemeth to haue moſt ſigne of holynes and goodnes ſeinge that it is all execrable or cutſed. Truely the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim wherewith the peſtilence is couered anoieth and greueth more greater tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that, that is ſeene open.</p>
            <p>Ite miſſa eſt. Amen <hi>3.</hi> Eſdras. <hi>4.</hi> chap. ¶ Super omnia vincit veritas. Aboue all thyng the truthe ouercometh.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>MDXLVII. ¶ Printed at Wittenbergs by Hans Lufte.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3923:32"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
